<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nevv shreds of the old snare Containing the apparitions of two new female ghosts. The copies of diuers letters of late intercourse concerning Romish affaires. Speciall indulgences purchased at Rome, granted to diuers English gentle-beleeuing Catholiques for their ready money. A catalogue of English nunnes of the late transportations within these two or three yeares. By Iohn Gee, Master of Arts, late of Exon-Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Gee, John, 1596-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01581</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11706</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103057</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838816</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838816</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3205</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01581)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3205)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1172:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nevv shreds of the old snare Containing the apparitions of two new female ghosts. The copies of diuers letters of late intercourse concerning Romish affaires. Speciall indulgences purchased at Rome, granted to diuers English gentle-beleeuing Catholiques for their ready money. A catalogue of English nunnes of the late transportations within these two or three yeares. By Iohn Gee, Master of Arts, late of Exon-Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Gee, John, 1596-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 121, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Dawson] for Robert Mylbourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Title page in red and black.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3205:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3205:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NEVV SHREDS OF THE OLD SNARE.</p>
            <p>CONTAINING
<list>
                  <item>The Apparitions of two new female Ghoſts.</item>
                  <item>The Copies of diuers Letters of late intercourſe
concerning Romiſh affaires.</item>
                  <item>Speciall Indulgences purchaſed at Rome, granted to diuers
Engliſh gentle-beleeuing Catholiques for their ready money.</item>
                  <item>A Catalogue of Engliſh Nunnes of the late
tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portations within theſe two or three yeares.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By IOHN GEE, Maſter of Arts, late of Exon-Colledge in
<hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Mylbourne.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:3205:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3205:2"/>
            <head>NEVV SHREDDS OF THE OLD SNARE broken by the foote of <hi>J.
G.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>The Induction.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome haue beene ſaid in the olde time vpon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of a
wound to haue beene healed by the ruſt of the weapon that gaue the wound; and
ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily for my part, after the ſpraine and diſlocation which I haue
ſuffered by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanglement in <hi>Popiſh Snares,</hi> nothing hath bin more
availeable to me for my perfect cure than the view and ſearch of thoſe
rotten ragged ſhredds of thoſe cords of vanitie and illuſion, which a
while dia hold mee captiue in the time of my weakeneſſe<pb facs="tcp:3205:3"/>The
beſt meanes therefore for the confirming of my ſelfe and arming others, is
and will be the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inquiring into the particular courſes of the great
ſeducing <hi>Maſters,</hi> eſpecially the <hi>Ieſuites;</hi> the
viewing and handling whereof vpon bare Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration without inference or
application, is ſufficient to ſhew the weakeneſs of thoſe twine-thred
bonds and Cob-web netts which they caſt over the ſilly fry of their
floating Diſciples.</p>
            <p>Since the inditing and publiſhing of my former Booke, called,
<hi>The Foote out of the Snare,</hi> I haue attained better information and
knowledge of diverſe particulars, which I thought fit to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to publique
view, for the better vnmasking of our <hi>Loiolan Mirabilaries,</hi> who as yet
impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently perſiſt to play their pranckes amongst vs.
<note place="margin">Theſe are <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſdem fils</hi> of the
ſame thred with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer woofe of the old <hi>Snare.</hi>
               </note> Some
ſnips of which their legerdemaine trickes, ſhufflingly twiſted and deeply
died in graine, here I diſplay in a new Webbe for the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>king out the <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> of the <hi>tyring
houſe</hi> of their former ſtage in array and manner as followeth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3205:3"/>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <l>All that can ſing or ſay,</l>
                  <l>Come and heare a Ieſuits play.</l>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Concluſion or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant to my former Booke, I made
bold to acquaint my Reader with <hi>Mary Wiltſhire,</hi> ſomtime enſnared
and cooped by a packe of <hi>Ieſuites</hi> or <hi>Prieſts,</hi> with the
engine of perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Apparitions; as alſo I gaue a touch in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of
M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
                  <hi>Bouchers</hi> daughter, which here accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my notice
followeth in particular.</p>
               <p>About ſome three yeares ſince <hi>Mary Boucher</hi> ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<hi>Butcher,</hi> daughter of <hi>Anne Boucher</hi> of the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of
<hi>London</hi> widdow (and Gentlewoman of good ſort) was entertained in the
ſervice of the Lady <hi>A.</hi> a <hi>Papist.</hi> But before ſhe went to
ſerue the ſaid Lady, M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
                  <hi>Boucher</hi> her mother told the Lady
<hi>A.</hi> that by no meanes ſhee would permit her daughter to liue with
her, if ſhee thought ſhee would be diverted from her Religion, ſhee being
then a good <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> The Lady promiſed that neither her ſelfe
nor any other ſhould haue to do<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3205:4"/>with her in that particular.
Yet there repairing often to this Ladies houſe M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Fiſher,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  <hi>Wainman,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ireland,</hi> Ieſuites, they were ſtill
buſie and labouring with this <hi>Mary Boucher</hi> to become a <hi>Romiſh
Catholicke,</hi> telling her that ſhee muſt be damn'd if ſhee did not
imbrace their Religion, and as for the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion they told
her that it was the deuils doctrine, brought in by <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> who
had conference with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and learnd of him every point of that beliefe
which the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> now retaine. For proofe hereof they ſhewed
her a Printed Booke wherein <hi>Luthers</hi> conference with the devill was at
large expreſſed. Vpon reading whereof the yong wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man did ſeeme to
ſtagger, and was much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed. And after a while theſe
<hi>Ieſuites</hi> came to her Miſtris houſe againe and then began to
tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and deale with her as before, and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Fiſher</hi> told her that
he knew better then her ſelfe what would become of her. Wee are Gods
<hi>Prophets</hi> (quoth he) wee can doe Miracles, and wee are inſpired with
divine Illuminations. It is revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto me that you muſt goe beyond the
Seas, and become a Nunne, which is to liue an Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call life, yea it is the
moſt excellent of all other kindes of liuing;
<note place="margin">A loud lewd <hi>Hyperbole.</hi>
                  </note>For it
obtaineth the ſame grace which is had in Baptiſme, and the entring into
that order doth take away all ſinne, both the fault and puniſhment, and
reſtoreth to the firſt ſtate of Innocency as Baptiſme doth. For proofe
where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he alledged vnto her diverſe ſentences preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be taken out
of the Fathers. This young <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3205:4"/>woman much amazed at him, told
him, that her Mother would never yeeld ſhee ſhould become a
<hi>Papist,</hi> much leſſe to be a Nunne and to leaue her Countrey. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  <hi>Fiſher</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Wainman</hi> both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, You muſt not
reſpect your mother in theſe matters. Shee is an Hereticke, and you ſhall
be Gods childe, and we would adviſe you never to ſee her any more. Theſe
things troubling and diſtempering the yong womans minde, ſhe found her
ſelfe ſcarce well, and then went and layd her downe vpon her bed, where
after ſhee had reſted her ſelfe a while, there comes into the chamber one
M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
                  <hi>Vauſe,</hi> a great Recuſant, and asked her how ſhee did, and
then came to her and did with ſomewhat ſtroke or rub her forehead. After
which time <hi>Mary Boucher</hi> felt her ſelfe very ill at eaſe and
diſtempered in her head. And about an half-houre after M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi>
                  <hi>Vauſe</hi> was departed from her, ſhee heard her chamber dore open, and
with that a great light flaſhed into the roome two or three times, which
ſhee thought ſome bodie did by way of ieſt or merriment, to make her
afraid. Wherevpon ſhee called on them not to affright her, for that ſhee
was not well. But forthwith came into the roome an apparitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſhape as of
a woman all in white, with countenance pale and wanne, with long treſſes of
haire hanging downe to her middle who ſtill made toward her; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at this
ſicke woman was much afraid. But this <hi>viſible</hi> approaching nearer
to her, bad her not to feare; for that ſhe came to her for her eternall good
and happineſſe. And with that the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3205:5"/>woman began
by degrees to remoue with her hand the haire from her face, and asked this
<hi>Mary</hi> whither ſhee knew who ſhee was; with that this
diſtreſſed <hi>Mary</hi> looked earneſtly on her, and then cryed out,
<hi>Oh my God-mother,</hi> and would haue gotten off from her bed to haue
aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked her bleſſing. But the other bad her lye ſtill and not ſtirre.
And then touching her with a hand cold as earth or iron, asked her where is
your mother, where is my husband, where are my children? And then told her
ſhee was come from <hi>Purgatory,</hi> where ſhe had long endured tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
and torment. And ſhee came to tell her how ſhee her God-daughter ſhould
eſcape the ſame. And then began to queſtion with her, what Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
ſhee was of: <hi>Mary Boucher</hi> told her, I am a <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> Oh
then quoth this Preaching goodly ghoſt, thou haſt no hope at all euer to
ſee heaven. Then it asked her againe, how many Sacraments there were. Shee
anſwered, two.
<note place="margin">A Cathechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Ghoſt.</note>Nay quoth the
Ghoſt, thou art deceived there are ſeaven. Then it asked her the third
time, whether ſhee did beleeue the point of <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation.</hi>
Shee anſwered, No. God-daughter quoth the Ghoſt, thou muſt beleeue that
eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally; For, for not beleeving that point, there is daily many hundreds
that are damned. And in this manner did this familiar informing, confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
Ghoſt continue for the ſpace of an houre or two queſtioning with <hi>Mary
Boucher,</hi> who lay in great heate and agony, ſweating and quaking vpon her
bed, no body all this while comming<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3205:5"/>neare &amp; diſturbing
them, which ſhee ſaith makes her ſince the rather beleeue it was a plot
deviſed and practiſed by the Prieſts, with the conſent of her
Miſtris: For in this Chamber where ſhee lay, there did vſe every
quarter-houre of the day to be ſome one or other comming in and out, being
the chamber where the children and Maid-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants lay, and had often
occaſion thither. When this Ghoſt had ſo long conferred with her, and was
taking her leaue, it willed her in this maner. By all meanes ſee that you
tell my children what you haue ſeene, and how their Mother appeared vnto you,
and what counſell ſhe hath given you. And then it vaniſhed away.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Ghoſt.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Shortly after the vaniſhing of this viſion, there comes into
<hi>Mary Bouchers</hi> chamber M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
                  <hi>Vauſe,</hi> and asked her how
ſhee fared. Shee anſwered her not well, but told her what had happened. Oh
then quoth M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
                  <hi>Vauſe,</hi> It is time for thee to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a good
<hi>Catholike;</hi> For aſſure thy ſelfe it was a ſpeciall favour and
mercy of God that thou ſhouldeſt haue ſuch a warning. And ſo giving her
more inſtructions to this purpoſe, went away.<note place="margin"> 
                     <hi>Exit
Vauſe. Intrat</hi> God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother. Nimble Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors know their <hi>Q.</hi>
                  </note>
And then appeared againe the Ghoſt and ſpake to her in this manner.
God-daughter thou maiſt thinke I loue thee well to come thus to thee and tell
thee what thou muſt doe to be ſaved, and not rather to haue ſpoken to one
of my owne chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. But I conſider that thou art ordained for an
extraordinary end, to be a Nunne, which is the happieſt life of all other.
For they that ſo liue are Saints vpon earth. The vow that is made by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3205:6"/> thoſe who enter into that order deſerveth the plenary
remiſſion of all ſinnes, and Iuſtification before God.
<note place="margin"> 
                     <hi>Iuſtification.</hi> Will the
<hi>Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> iuſtifie this for ghoſtly doctrine? A bold Ghoſt
alluding to S. <hi>Pauls</hi> inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias.</hi> Act.
22.</note> And therefore God-daughter if any holy man perſwade thee to that
courſe of life, accept of it, and I would haue thee to repaire vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  <hi>Ireland</hi> a Prieſt, and he will direct thee in this courſe.
Whatſoever he biddeth thee to doe, refuſe it not. And ſo the Ghoſt
vaniſhed the ſecond time. And in the whole appeared vnto her aboue a dozen
times, which ſo amazed her, that ſhee was not her ſelfe a long time
after.</p>
               <p>Though this viſion was privately Acted, yet the noiſe of it
was bruted abroad and came to the eare of M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
                  <hi>Boucher</hi> the Mother,
who therevpon came to the houſe of her Miſtris to ſpeake with her
daughter, but being forſooth an Hereticke might not be admitted after long
waiting to queſtion with her owne child about this ſtrange newes. Nay the
daughter her ſelfe vpon freſh ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion hereof was perſwaded by
thoſe in the houſe to eſtrange her ſelfe toward her owne mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who
notwithſtanding preſſing on, did at length ſpeake with her Miſtris
the Lady of the houſe, and in her daughters preſence vpbrayded them with
theſe Colluſions, and telling the Lady that ſhee thought her to be of
better vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding then to put any beliefe in ſuch devices, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
moreover, that it was great wrong to the dead Lady to be thus acted as being in
<hi>Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> when as ſhe was a woman ſo vertuous and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious,
that it is not to be doubted but that ſhee is in heaven. And though vſing
great importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3205:6"/>to haue her daughter home, ſhee could
not obtaine it, wherevpon ſhee vſed further meanes by complaining vnto
ſome in high place and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, for the reſcuing of her child out of
the poſſeſſion of thoſe who had thus deluded her: But vſing all the
helpes ſhee could, it was more than halfe a yeare ere ſhee could get her
daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter home to her. And within a weeke after her daughters being with her,
ſome of theſe ghoſtly Fathers that ſent this ghoſt to her, did by the
conveiance of a private Letter call her off againe, ſo that ſhe made an
eſcape from her Mother and flew the ſecond time to their lure. And to
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent her Mothers recovering of her againe, they determined to ſet her
packing beyond the Seas, there to be Nunnified. To which end they ſcratcht vp
by their <hi>Catholicke</hi>-hookes the ſum of threeſcore pounds to line
this new Nunne. This comming to her Mothers notice, whetted her endeavours to
regaine her childe, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly ſhee ſpake to ſome who ſhee knew
had intereſt in thoſe that robd her of her daughter, threatning that ſhee
would complaine to the <hi>Higheſt,</hi> and declare their deceitfull lewd
cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. This ſharpe ingredient wrought ſo well, that the voyage was
ſtayed and her daughter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored. Who ſince being in her Mothers tuition
and receiving due inſtruction, hath by Gods bleſſing pulled her <hi>Foote
out of the Snare,</hi> well ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and leaving the vanitie of
<hi>Popery.</hi> Shee is now married and dwelleth neare
<hi>Bainards-Caſtle</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> where of late I viſited her to
informe<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3205:7"/>my ſelfe the better of the truth of theſe
particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. And within theſe very few dayes ſhee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing demanded in my
hearing, what meanes ſhee thinketh to haue beene vſed to make thoſe
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritions to her, and diſquiets in her, ſhee ſaith; Shee thinketh in
her conſcience ſome of thoſe things could not be done without Witchcraft,
or ſome ſtrange helpe by the devill.
<note place="margin">The particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parition are
incntioned in my former Booke.</note>In which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion I muſt needs ſay
ſhee doth concurre with <hi>Mary Wiltſhire,</hi> who not long ſince in my
hearing repeated ſuch apparitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s made to her to the ſame end, did with
great aſſeverance expreſſe that ſhee verily thinketh that they who
made the appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> dealt by Sorcery or ſuch
indirect deviliſh meanes.</p>
               <p>I doubt I ſhall now ſure vndergoe the <hi>Ferula</hi> of our
grand pedanticke Maſters the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> for telling ſo many tales
out of the ſchoole: which their Anger will be the more implacable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
they know my informations to be good, my relations to be warrantable, and the
very cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of them to trench vpon the reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe who
would be thought ſo wiſe and vncontrouleable, that they deſerue to hold
the whole Chriſtian world in pupillage and pillage. But for my part I muſt
ſpare them never a whit the more. The neceſſitie of any dutie
ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the weight of their menaces. As he that hath beene incited to hold
out a Caſtle muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly againſt the lawfull owners and gouernors
thereof, when he ſeeth his fault and hath ſlipped away from his fellow
Mutiners, is in duty bound<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3205:7"/>not to favour thoſe his
<hi>quondam</hi>-Mates, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the better demonſtration of his
allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, is to diſcover what he can the practiſes of their
combination, and to lead others on to the battery of that hold in ſuch places
where he by experience knowes it to lye weake and beſt aſſaileable: So I
am ſo farre from repenting of the former declarations made by me, out of
conſcience and truth againſt thoſe that poſſeſſe many a ſecret
hold in the Territories of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Dominions, ſeaſing vpon the
hearts and houſes of many, and captivating them within a combination, in
oppoſition againſt our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on eſtabliſhed, and diſcontent
againſt the courſe of our civill eſtate and Lawes; that I cannot but goe
on in vſing my beſt memory to recollect what I knew, and meanes to inquire
what for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly I knew not, that might conduce to the further diſplay of their
practiſes. I confeſſe I ſpeake ſtones, and lay inke and gall on their
tettars. But, <hi>Dicatur veritas, rumpatur invidia;</hi> Let the Truth be
ſpread, and their Envy burſt it Gall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:3205:8"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The ſecond Comodie of a <hi>Female Apparition,</hi>
acted by the thrice honourable Company of <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> Players to the
<hi>Popes</hi> Holines.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ieſuites</hi> are in at all
games.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bout <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt 1623. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Fiſher</hi> and
M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Wainman, Ieſuits,</hi> came to a <hi>Romiſh Recuſants</hi>
houſe in <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rey,</hi> where ſoiourned a young Gentlewoman, one M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi>
                  <hi>Francis Peard,</hi> whoſe parents being dead, ſhee had her portion of
goods in her own hands, which portion (as I am credibly informed) was aboue a
thouſand pounds. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Fiſher</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Wain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> laboured
to perſwade this Gentlewoman to become a <hi>Romiſh Catholicke,</hi> and at
length prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and perverted her; which done M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Fiſher</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  <hi>Wainman</hi> began to conſider how they might worke her out of her
moneys, which being ſo round a ſumme, they laboured to get this fat Fiſh
into their Nett.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A <hi>Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bankes</hi>
Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>Maſter <hi>Wainman</hi> begins here to Act his part, and
firſt comes to her by himſelfe and ſaith; <hi>Oh Miſtris Francis, what
a glorious ſight did I behold the laſt night. At midnight being in my bed I
lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake and began to ſay over my Breviary,<note place="margin">The
<hi>Breviary</hi> is attractiue of <hi>Virgins</hi> in the night as well as in
the day.</note> which I had no ſooner done, but there appeared vnto me a
beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Virgin like your ſelfe, all in white, glittering like
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3205:8"/>an Angell, and ſaid vnto me, Behold I am ſuch a one,
whom you being my ghostly Father perſwaded to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Nunne, and now I
appeare to giue you thanks. For ſince my departure out of this world, I
raigne in glory with the Virgin</hi> Mary. <hi>All the tongues in the world
cannot expreſſe that which I now poſſeſſe. There is a Gentlewoman
you lately perſwaded to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Catholicke, M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi>
                  </hi> Francis Peard:
<hi>Oh perſwade her to the ſame life that I led in the heavenly
Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie at</hi> Bruxells: <hi>Shee will without doubt be a good
Saint.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Oh thrice bleſſed
<hi>Ieſuite.</hi>
                  </note>This <hi>viſible</hi> having thus ſpoken vnto M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  <hi>Wainman,</hi> It gaue him (as he ſaid) three <hi>Benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and
vaniſhed away.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Wainman</hi> the <hi>Precurſor</hi>
vnto <hi>Fiſher</hi> to beat game into his Nett.</note>After the narration of
this <hi>viſion</hi> made to M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
                  <hi>Peard,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Wainman</hi>
began to exhort her to <hi>Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> and vſed diverſe Arguments for
the alluring her to ſuch courſe of liuing. And ſo left the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman
for that time, who as yet was vnreſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved what to doe. The weeke following
M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Fiſher</hi> perſwaded this Gentlewoman to come to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi>
and appointed her to lodge in a <hi>Popiſh</hi> houſe in <hi>Drury
lane,</hi> and told her ſhee ſhould there heare a very excellent
<hi>Sermon.</hi> According to his directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhee came to the appointed
houſe in <hi>London,</hi> and the day following heard a Sermon preached by a
<hi>Ieſuite,</hi> whoſe name ſhee could not learne; but his Text was
taken out of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. <hi>And for Virgins a Commandement of our Lord
I haue not, but Counſell I giue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as having obteined mercy of our Lord to
be faithfull</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In which Sermon he tooke occaſion to handle the point of
<hi>Vowes,</hi> and ſaid, that to <hi>vow Chaſtitie</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3205:9"/>and to liue vnmarried, was an Angelicall life vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, reſembling
the ſtate of the bleſſed in heaven, where they
<note place="margin">Math. 22.</note>
                  <hi>neither marry nor be
married, but are as the Angels of God in heaven.</hi> And ſpake particularly
of <hi>Nunnes,</hi> that as they ſing in Gods quire here vpon earth, ſo
they ſhall ſing a ſong of ioy in heaven which none can ſing but they;
and ſhall be crowned with a ſpeciall Crowne of glory, which none can weare
but they.</p>
               <p>This Sermon much inflamed the Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with zeale to become
a <hi>Nunne:</hi> which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher</hi> well perceived. And the night
following af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this Gentlewoman had beene in her bed ſome houre or two,
there ſeemed to be a great light in her Chamber, which at the firſt
behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereof aſtoniſhed her, and then preſently after appeared vnto
her, a ſhape like vnto a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man all in white: from her face ſeemed to come
little ſtreames of fire, or glittering light. This <hi>Woman-ſhape</hi>
firſt bad her not be afraid, for ſhee came to her with a meſſage from
heaven, and ſaid her name was S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Lucy,</hi> who being borne of honorable
Parents, and of a great Familie, had great riches left vnto her by her friends;

<note place="margin">The fruitfull vſefull part of a ghoſtly
Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is in the Application.</note>which riches fearing leaſt they ſhould
be an hinderance to her in the proceſſe of godlineſſe, ſhe beſtowed
all vpon the poore and liued a Monaſticall life, by meanes whereof ſhee is
now one of the moſt glorious Saints in heaven. And then ſaid this crafty
<hi>viſion</hi> to the Gentlewoman, Doe you alſo diſpoſe of thoſe
worldly things that you haue to the poore, and toward religious Vſes, and goe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3205:9"/>your wayes and liue a religious life amongſt the good
company of <hi>Virgins</hi> at <hi>Bruxells,</hi> and ſo ſhall you be
ſure to be ſaved, and freed from the fire of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> which
otherwiſe you cannot eſcape. And ſo this <hi>viſion</hi> left her.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cogging were la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e, if dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing did not follow.</note>The next morning
came to viſit her M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Fiſher</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Wainman,</hi> to whom
ſhee preſently began to relate what ſhee had ſeene that night, and that
S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Lucy</hi> had appeared to her and talked with her.
<note place="margin">The poore Proteſtant Heretickes haue no
ſuch ſweet <hi>viſions.</hi>
                  </note>Oh what a happy woman are you quoth
M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher.</hi> You may ſee what it is to be a <hi>Catholicke</hi>
and to be of our Church. Thus doth God worke his Miracles amongſt vs daily,
and by ſuch <hi>viſions</hi> doth God commonly reveale himſelfe vnto vs.
What will you now doe then, ſaid M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Wainman?</hi> Will you not become a
<hi>Nunne?</hi> Yes forſooth, ſaid the Gentlewoman, I will be adviſed by
you. So then they wiſhed her to get her moneys rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and one of them would
be her Conductor to <hi>Bruxells.</hi> But, quoth M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Wainman,</hi> you had
beſt giue an hundred pounds preſently to poore <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes</hi> in
thankfulnes for S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Lucyes</hi> good will towards you.<note place="margin">The fine w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Lucyes</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants pay at entrance, an hundred pounds.</note> Yea, ſaid M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Fiſher,</hi> that indeed will be a worke
meritorious. Then ſaid M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Wain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> You had beſt put it into our
hands, and wee will diſtribute it where we find moſt fit.<note place="margin"> 
                     <hi>Quiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſibi proximus.</hi> He is an ill
<hi>Cooke</hi> that licks not his ovvne fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. </note> To all this the
innocent Gentlewoman with little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine yeelded, and within few dayes after
delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them an hundred pounds. Shortly after they came to her and told her,
that they muſt haue an hundred pounds more to ſend over to the Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery
before her,<note place="margin">Hard Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act a ſecond fine. Why
ſhould they not be ſued in Court of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore it?</note> to
make proviſion of ſome ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſeries<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3205:10"/>againſt her
comming. The which hundred pounds they likewiſe tugged out of her hands; and
for the ſpace of a quarter of a yeare, theſe two
Maſter-<hi>Ieſuites,</hi> like two cunning old Gray-hounds that could well
ſerue one anothers turne for the catching the poore hare, with ſome other
Iourney-men of their trade, made great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to and fro this Gentlewoman, and
every one of them began to plucke a feather from the plume of her eſtate.</p>
               <p>Shee ſeeing and plainly perceiving that they made Religion a
ſtalking horſe to intend their owne profit, began to take conſideration
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to meditate on their practiſing, aſſuring her ſelfe that
they aymed at nothing more than to cheate her of her moneys and goods.
<note place="margin">Experience deare bought.</note> And
ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly weighing the particulars of the appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on preſented to her
in <hi>Drury lane,</hi> ſhee concluded it muſt needs be ſome iugling
tricke deviſed by thoſe Maſters, and aſſiſted by ſome in the
houſe. In briefe, ſhee reſolved to ſhake off her gracious grand-Fathers
the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> and ſo to bid her new Gueſt
the <hi>Roman Religion</hi> fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
               <p>By the like Pageant or tricke of legerdemaine was <hi>Elizabeth
Powell</hi> of <hi>Holborne</hi> within this tweluemoneth befopped with
Viſions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations, and perſwaded to become a <hi>Nunne,</hi> whom of
late the <hi>Prieſts</hi> haue packed over to ſome <hi>Monaſtery,</hi>
giving her belike not ſo long a time of deliberation to bethinke her ſelfe;
or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther her ghoſtly Father M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Musket</hi> is a man ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3205:10"/>nimbler than his Copes-mates. He was the Maſter-gamſter
(as I haue heard) who fetcht o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver this ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Powell,</hi> but
in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he played his part vpon the Stage, I cannot yet learne.</p>
               <p>As concerning their other Impoſture and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenage of M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi>
                  <hi>Peard,</hi> I ſee no reaſon but that theſe <hi>Ieſuites</hi>
ſhould be ſued; Firſt vpon an Action of Account, how they haue
diſpoſed theſe ſummes, being committed to them in truſt, and limited
to others vſes. Nor would I be the Advocate for them if they were ſued in
the <hi>Starre-chamber</hi> for <hi>Subornation, lewd practiſe and
Coſenage,</hi> having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into ſuch a combination, and executed the
ſame by ſuch cheating, ſhuffling, and Comicall an Engine. I haue heard
that in that high Court within theſe three yeares ſome combining chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
Companions, haue beene queſtioned for ſtripping a ſimple credulous man
out of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vennues, by ſetting vp one of their company in a Taverne to Act
a Commanding part over the reſt of that good fellowſhip, who by their
device ſhould haue ſuch authoritie, that none of the reſt might diſobey
whatſoever he impoſed on them.
<note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fooled.</note>This Commander they ſtiled by
the mightie name of <hi>Captaine Gogge,</hi> who vpon pretence of this power,
made one of his ſilly Companions to ſet his hand to a writing there
brought, which proued a Releaſe of right in certaine Lands, which for ought I
heare could neuer be recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againe. But the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> devices are
more refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this onely by the ſpirit of liquor and bond
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3205:11"/>of roaring good fellowſhippe, but theirs by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
divine inſpirations, viſible meſſengers, and audible meſſages from
heaven. And what perſwaſiue power is there betweene the bluſtring
Commands of any <hi>Gog</hi> or <hi>Magog</hi> in compariſon of the ſweet
inſinuations of a <hi>Virgin-Saint,</hi> imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in ſome ſort the
<hi>Angell Gabriell</hi> in ſpeaking to a Virgin and comforming her ſelfe
to her own name in the manner of her apparition, flaſhing out rayes or beames
of light. <hi>O Luciam lucidiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam,</hi> or rather <hi>O luculentam
fraudem, O lutulen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſcelus!</hi> A bold, palpable, dirtie Impoſture. And
if wee conſider this kinde of knauery in the higheſt pitch of it, me
thinkes theſe lewd pagen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teeres ſhould be queſtioned alſo in ſome
<hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Court</hi> for <hi>Prophanation</hi> of heaven and
holy things, making them by ſuch devices little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than Theatricall and
fabulous tricks to get money and ineſcate poore deceived ſoules. I know not
whither any of our <hi>Biſhops Courts,</hi> or <hi>high Commiſsion</hi> doe
take cogniſance of ſuch kind of abuſes, but if they doe, thoſe holy,
heauenly, Virginall, Monaſticall, fantaſticall, ſophiſticall Contrivers
and Actors will cut out worke for them to ſpend ſome time in cenſure.</p>
               <p>But now I bethinke my ſelfe how deeply I am miſtaken, I had
forgotten that the ſuperex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, tranſcendent, exorbitant order of the
<hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites,</hi> is not ſubiect to any but their owne ſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall
Superiours. What talke you of our Courts of Iuſtice in <hi>England?</hi> They
haue no more power over theſe exempts, than the <hi>King of Kalle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:3205:11"/>hath over the <hi>Virginian Toma-Coma.</hi> All
<hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Prieſts</hi> forſooth are exempt from ſecular hands, and
Ieſuites <hi>Exemptiſsimi</hi> from the ſecular Prieſts. The
Conſiſtories of our Biſhops can doe no Acts but nullities againſt any
of theſe; For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing they doe is voyd <hi>ipſo facto, quia per non
Iudicem.</hi> Ours are not Eccleſiaſticall Iudges, nor haue any
Iuriſdiction, becauſe not derived from the <hi>Well-head at Rome,</hi> nor
imparted by him who hath the keyes of all Church-lockes at his girdle, and
ſetting his hands by his ſide brauely ſayes, <hi>Data eſt mihi omnis
poteſtas in Coelo &amp; in terra. All power is given to me in heaven and in
earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now for manner of cleanly conveyance of this
buſineſſe, nay, in theſe manifold <hi>Pageants</hi> of heavenly
<hi>viſibles,</hi> I haue thought with my ſelfe diverſe times to what
kind of operation I ſhould referre it. Somewhat I thinke may be done this way
by Paper Lanthornes or tranſparent Glaſſes to eradiate &amp; redouble
light, &amp; caſt out painted ſhapes by multiplication of the <hi>ſpecies
viſibiles,</hi> &amp; artificiall directing of refractions. And for the
<hi>Actor</hi> that puts life into this mimicall Artillery by motion and voice,
that may be done by ſome nimble handed and footed <hi>Nouice Ieſuitable
Boy,</hi> that can as eaſily put on the perſon of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Lucy,</hi> or
<hi>The virgin Mary,</hi> as a Play-boy can act winged <hi>Mercury,</hi> or
Eagle mounted <hi>Ganimedes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> being or having <hi>Actors</hi> of
ſuch dexteritie, I ſee no reaſon but that they ſhould ſet vp a
company for themſelues, which ſurely will put down <hi>The Fortune,
Red-Bull, Cock-pit, &amp; Globe.</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:3205:12"/>Onely three exceptions
ſome make againſt them which perhaps may make their Cuſtomers after a
while ſome what coole and thinly to frequent them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tautologie.</note>
                  <note place="margin">It
ſeemes by want of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie the <hi>Poet</hi> is drawne dry.</note>One is,
that the plots of their Comedies twang all vpon one ſtring, apparitions of
the ſame kind, their Actors having little or no varietie of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe. In
all theſe three or foure Playes, none comes in Acting but <hi>A Woman, A
Woman, A Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> arrayed in <hi>white, white, white.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">I am ſo chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to plead for them
without a Fee.</note>But I anſwer for them; That perhaps may be excuſed,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſpectators are women, and ſo ſhee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conſort
beſt with her owne ſexe. Neither haue they much varietie of apparell. One
<hi>white robe</hi> and no other habit in three ſeverall Playes. White from
<hi>Heaven,</hi> and white from <hi>Purgatory.</hi> I will be ſo kinde as to
anſwer for them in caſe of <hi>Tautologie,</hi> or want of varietie, with
that advice which was once giuen to an <hi>Orator,</hi> who being to make an
Oration before a curious Auditory, and belabouring his memory with often
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning it by heart, at length loathed his owne worke by often hearing it, and
therefore diſtruſted the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditories acceptation; Whereto his Friend made
anſwer; <hi>Though you by often repeating it are weary, yet to them it will
be freſh enough, becauſe they ſhall heare it but once.</hi> So though
themſelues are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the dulnes of the ſame tricke which they act
often, yet their comfort is, that it is repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but to one, and ſo the
leſſe ſpread, and every time of repetition tis preſented to a new
ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor that never ſaw it before, to whom it may well be freſh and
welcome.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:3205:12"/>
                  <note place="margin">2.
Incongrui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note>The ſecond Obiection is <hi>Incongruitie,</hi> the
<hi>Poet</hi> ſeeming worthy to be quarrelled with all for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing to
ſend one in a <hi>white robe</hi> from the ſmoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie burning Kitchen of
<hi>Purgatory.</hi> The Tel-tale from that place ſhould rather haue come in a
ſcorched ſheete all torned to tinder. But hereto I anſwer for our good
<hi>Poets</hi> the <hi>Ieſuites.</hi> If the ſheet had beene burnt to
tinder, it would not haue hung together, and ſo all the device had falne in
pieces.</p>
               <p>But ſtay <hi>Sir Poet,</hi> one <hi>word</hi> more concerning
the title of <hi>Incongruitie.</hi> What <hi>Decorum</hi> is it to bring from
<hi>Purgatory</hi> her that Acted <hi>God-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> who was knowne to the
<hi>Spectatrix</hi> to haue beene a <hi>Proteſtant:</hi> whereas all thoſe
that build <hi>Purgatory,</hi> doe intend it for a <hi>hot Inne</hi> for the
<hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholickes</hi> onely. But no <hi>Hereticke</hi> may haue the honor
to ſmell of thoſe flames, but are beat downe with a Club to hell in
poſt-haſt with out baiting by the way. Hereto I anſwer, that theſe
<hi>Actors</hi> would giue out that ſhee dyed a <hi>Romanist,</hi> and hope
they may pretend ſo, becauſe ſhe liued and dyed a very vertuous life:
<hi>Godlines</hi> being a proper Priviledge entailed to the
<hi>Romaniſts,</hi> who ſeeing any Ship of great burthen, (any great
lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man) paſſing to his Haven, giue ayme pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently and ſay, it is
ours;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> The <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> Cathech.
<hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 17.</note> thus dealt <hi>Puteanus</hi> the
Provinciall of the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> with him, who was <hi>veré
Ieſuit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>-maſtix,</hi> religious
and renowned M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Beza;</hi> and as cunningly or knaviſhly dealt
<hi>foule-mouth'd</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Musket,</hi> and doting <hi>Doctor
Kelliſon,</hi> both <hi>Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,</hi> with the late reverend and learned
<hi>Biſhop of</hi> 
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:3205:13"/>
                  <hi>London.</hi> But <hi>Fallitur cum
ſua tota cater ua Diabolus.</hi> The deuill and all his rout were much
deceived. They dyed in a conſtant beliefe, perſwaſion, and profeſſion
of that holy Truth of God, in defence whereof they ſtood both by writing
&amp; ſpeaking againſt the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to make vp your mouth againſt all diſtaſt of
<hi>Incongruitie,</hi> I ſay the <hi>Poet</hi> kept within his Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. For
he well knew that deepe paſſions, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially affright and
aſtoniſhing admiration, doe for the time bereaue and ſuſpend exact
inquiring diſcourſe. Well might he preſume that the ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tator being a
Woman would not be too full of true <hi>Syllogiſme,</hi> and being
poſſeſſed with admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her revi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>'d God-mother, would not be too buſie in <hi>Theologicall
Queres,</hi> how ſhee was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of that place from whence ſhee came to
vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit her God-daughter.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">3. Deare price.</note>The third abatement of
the honor and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of this Scenicall company is, that <hi>they make
their ſpectators pay to deare for their Income.</hi> Repreſentations and
Apparitions from the dead might be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ene farre cheaper at other Play-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. As for example, the
<hi>Ghoſt in Hamblet, Don Andreas Ghoſt in Hieronimo.</hi> As for flaſhes
of light, we might ſee very cheape in the Comedie of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus</hi> and
<hi>Thiſbe,</hi> where one comes in with a Lanthorne and Acts
<hi>Mooneſhine.</hi> But here for a Comedie conſiſting of one
<hi>Scene,</hi> and one <hi>Actor,</hi> tis very deare market to pay an hundred
pounds for entrance, and beſides that another hundred pounds for ſitting in
a boxe neere the Stage.<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3205:13"/>But here I anſwer for them (though
I thinke I ſhall haue little thanke for my paines of them) that they having
but one Spectator, muſt haue as much of that one as if they had an whole
Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter full. The <hi>Lawyer</hi> that pleads at Barre for his Client, will
not therefore abate any thing of his Fee becauſe the Auditory is ſmall or
the Iudges few, his ſtudy and preparation being the ſame.</p>
               <p>Moreover, though there be but one Actor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing here vpon the
Stage, yet you muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that here are diverſe others within the
ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring-houſe, that take a great deale of paines to proiect the plot, to
inſtruct the Actor, and to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him with habit and ornament. And who
can tell how many ſharers there are that muſt take part of that which is
paid? Wherein I hope that theſe two <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> F.
<hi>Fiſher,</hi> and F. <hi>Wainman,</hi> men of extraordinary action, haue a
treble or quatriple ſhare each of them, as being the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall over-ruling
Maſters. Would any man thinke that <hi>Burbege</hi> ſhould be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent with
a ſingle ſhare, who was the flower and life of his company, the
<hi>Loadſtone</hi> of the Auditory, and the <hi>Roſeius</hi> of the
Stage?</p>
               <p>Another matter more troubled my curioſitie, where and of what
Maſter they learned theſe trickes of <hi>legerdemaine.</hi> I alwayes
thought they had their rudiments from ſome iugling <hi>Hocas Pocas</hi> in a
quart pot.
<note place="margin">A man of great name and fame.</note>At length
I learnd that one of them, namely, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Wainman,</hi> alias M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  <hi>Wright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> alias M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Wood,</hi> alias M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Peacock,</hi> alias
M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> alias M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Read,</hi> alias M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Frye,</hi> alias
M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>French</hi> 
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:3205:14"/>(I thinke he taketh eight names to
anſwer to the eight <hi>Beatitudines</hi>) had beene heretofore the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor
and Diſciple of a grand Maſter, notorious in the peoples reputation for
ſtrange feates. And beſides I learned that this ſaid <hi>Wainman</hi> had
long ſince ſome trickes of cleanly conveyance, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he brought a whole
waine-load from <hi>Briſtow,</hi> where he made himſelfe very famous by
profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that he could make the <hi>Philoſophers ſtone,</hi> and
turne any mettall into gold; But he ſo turned o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the money of a Knight
thereabouts by <hi>Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, Calcination, Proiection,</hi> and
<hi>Cohobbation,</hi> that the Knight might well haue wiſhed this
<hi>Mountebank</hi> had ſtudied leſſe the <hi>Chimicall Trade,</hi>
vnleſſe he had left more fruit of his labours by <hi>proiection</hi>
behinde him.<note place="margin">An <hi>Alchymist</hi> vſually an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers his
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded ſcholler with expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Proiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and tells him
the more his <hi>Materials</hi> be multiplied, the ſtronger will the
<hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection</hi> be; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if it come to the mountenance of an
hundred pounds. <hi>Vid.</hi> The Play of the <hi>Alchymiſt.</hi>
                  </note> And
yet haue I heard he was not vtterly vnfruitfull there. For how ſoever his
Inventions proued abortiue concerning the <hi>Philoſophers ſtone,</hi> yet
he leſt ſome evidence of bringing forth ſome worke of perfection, or
ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imperfection by other kinde of ſtones; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which imployment
of <hi>Multiplication,</hi> I could make a <hi>Quere</hi> how it agrees with
his Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, or with the ſublimated quinteſſence of his
Ieſuiticall order. Whoſe holy function would be blaſted and crackt in
ſunder by any Matrimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Coniunction? If himſelfe were to anſwer, he
could eaſily put it off with ſome equivocating tricke,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> of
<hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</hi>
                  </note> like his brother <hi>Ignatian,</hi> who being
exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined vpon oath whether he were a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, No; and
after ſaid, he meant he was not a <hi>Prieſt of Baal.</hi> And ſo aske
this man whether it<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3205:14"/>accord with his Father-hood to be as
fruitfull in the fleſh as in the ſpirit, he will haue ſome ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
ſhift that will make all ſound, without vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Text <hi>Creſcite
&amp; multiplicamini &amp; replete terram.</hi> Gen. 1. 28.</p>
               <p>That which I would now haue you obſerue out of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  <hi>Fiſher</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Wainmans</hi> pretty iugling practiſes is, with
what creeping ſly ſtealth the <hi>Maſter-Gameſters</hi> the
<hi>Ieſuites</hi> doe driue the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male <hi>Partridges</hi> into their Nett
by the helpe of the ſetting Dogge of ſneaking <hi>Viſions</hi> and
<hi>Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſmes.</hi> Or to come nearer the habit of this <hi>Scene;</hi>
When I conſider their carriage and wily beguiling conveyance, me thinkes I
behold the cunning <hi>Fowler,</hi> ſuch as I haue knowne in the
Fenne-Countries, and els-where, that doe ſhoot at Woodcockes, Snipes, and
wilde Fowle, by ſneaking behind a painted cloth which they carry before them,
having pictured in it the ſhape of a Horſe, which while the ſilly Fowle
gazeth on, ſhee is knockt downe with <hi>Hale-ſhot,</hi> and ſo put in
the Fowlers-budget. Oh the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall incomparable engine of Ieſuiticall
Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, the painted <hi>Hobby-horſe</hi> of Saint-like Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritions from
Heaven or <hi>Purgatory!</hi> Whilſt the ſilly Bird gazeth with rapting
admiration; <hi>Bounce ſayes the Ieſuites Gunne, Thou art mine,</hi> and
takes them by the Coxcombe, and packes them by dozens to ſend by the
<hi>Poulterers</hi> to be put in Coopes at <hi>Bruxells,</hi> and elſe-where.

<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quó pulchrius E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> charius.</hi>
                  </note>Wherein I commend
their skill in their Trade, <pb n="24" facs="tcp:3205:15"/>that they chuſe as neare as
they can thoſe fowle that are fatte and faire of feather. If a leane one come
in the way, the fatter ſhall beare it out. In the one they haue a pretence of
<hi>Wiſedome,</hi> in the other of <hi>Charitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But oh, the profound Policie which our <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natians</hi> vſe
for the confirmation and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Religion, conſiſting
in theſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlatiue proiects and practiſes, wherein they goe as farre
beyond their fellow <hi>Prieſts,</hi> as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Stevens</hi> galloping
Croſſe beyond a penny Palme Croſſe;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> The
Foot out of the Snare. <hi>pag.</hi> 70.</note> or F. <hi>Garnets</hi> little
ſtraw beyond all the Wheat-ſheaues in <hi>England.</hi> What infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
arguments are theſe ſtrange Apparitions to vphold <hi>Faith?</hi> The
<hi>Sorbonites</hi> in truth vpbraid the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> with a Doctrine,
that they hold it lawfull <hi>to forge a Miracle for the furtherance of their
Religion:</hi> Why ſhould not I thinke, that they hold it as lawfull
ſometimes to forge a <hi>viſion,</hi> for the better maintenance of their
<hi>Catholicke</hi> cauſe? I remember how the <hi>Sorbon</hi> concluded by a
Decree of the yeare 1554. and 1564.<note place="margin">The <hi>Sorbons</hi>
cenſure of the <hi>Ieſuites.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hac ſocietas periculoſa in
negotio fidei, vana, nugax, mendax, pacis Eccleſiae perturbatiua, Monaſtica
Religionis euerſura, &amp; magis in deſtructionem quam in edificationem
ordinata,</hi> &amp;c. Surely if bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the ſame ſeame cenſure thus
hardly of them for their lowd lying, let none wonder if I begin to ſentence
them for the onely Cogging Impoſtors of theſe times, ſcandalizing the
name of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> with moſt impious inventions, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>befitting
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3205:15"/>any though deſperate Hereticke, and arguing little
leſſe than Atheiſticall prophanes. As for their <hi>viſions,</hi> and
ſuch like ayery Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banke <hi>Hobgoblin-ſtuffe,</hi> I ſay
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Fooles may be frighted with
Hagges, and Fairies; men of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding know it is but knavery.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:3205:16"/>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:3205:16"/>
            <head>THE COPPIES OF DIVERS LETTERS OF Late Intercourſe concerning
<hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Affayres.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Coppie of a Letter (the Originall whereof is in my hands)
ſent from <hi>Rome</hi> to F. COLLETON, Arch-Prieſt, <hi>alias</hi>
Arch-deacon of LONDON.</head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ather <hi>Colleton</hi> we receiued your Letters dated the
xxix<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> wherein you write of Prince CHARLES his going for
<hi>Spaine.</hi>
                        <pb n="28" facs="tcp:3205:17"/>The newes was here before your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
and there is no doubt but we ſhall now worke all things to our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.
Father <hi>Pitts</hi> is ſent from his <hi>Holines</hi> with Letters to the
King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> vpon his return we ſhall heare more. His
<hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines</hi> hath created 3 new <hi>Biſhops:</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Biſhop</hi>
is <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> and comes ſhortly into
<hi>England:</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Bath</hi> and F. <hi>Iohn Roch</hi> are made
<hi>Biſhops,</hi> the one of <hi>Gortyna,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of
<hi>Cydonea,</hi> and are to be ſent into <hi>Ireland.</hi> If matters
ſucceed well, there will be other new <hi>Biſhops</hi> and an
<hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop</hi> ſent over for the propagating of true diſcipline in
your Kingdome: and for thoſe who haue now indured the heat of the day will be
the freer paſſage to Eccleſiaſticall dignitie. His <hi>Holines</hi>
would haue you adviſe thoſe who are ſubordinate to you, that they walke
warily, to be as ſecret as formerly, the eaſier (as he ſayth) may they
worke their owne ends. He would haue none puffed vp, or ſwell with
ſenſuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, but remaine yet mortified, that humilitie, charitie,
obedience, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation,<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3205:17"/>zeale of ſoules may be moſt
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. As water doth more inflame the Smiths forge, as repugnance doth
ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the Lyons courage, as tartnes eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the languiſhing appetite: ſo
will it imbolden and ſtrengthen the <hi>Heretickes,</hi> if they know they
are to finde oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their naturall inclinations, and
ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualitie. <hi>Religion</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Divineſt of all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines
S. Thomas of Aquin</hi>)<note place="margin">I had thought S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                           <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                           <hi>Bernard</hi> and ſome other of the Fathers had
beene as divine as He.</note> 
                        <hi>muſt haue neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Policie, Tunc
enim piae ſuae obſervantiae ex maiori diſcretione ordinatae ſunt ad
finem religionis.</hi> For then her pious obſervantio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s through more
diſcretion are directed to the end of Religion.</p>
                     <p>Our <hi>Colledge</hi>-money from the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> of
<hi>England</hi> comes in ſlowly: There is three hundred pounds of what we
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to receiue behinde. Wee muſt intreat you to call vpon them, and
if <hi>T. M.</hi> be in <hi>England,</hi> acquaint him with it. I haue written
hereof to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Wright,</hi> and haue deſired him to ſend vs an hundred
pounds from his ſtocke: he knowes where to receiue it againe. Father
<hi>Spen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> I heare hath laine ſicke this great<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3205:18"/>while at <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> I pray God ſend him luſtie againe good
man. We heare that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Daniell</hi> (whom Father <hi>Sweet</hi> knowes
well) hath an ancient Manuſcript called the <hi>Hiſtory of S.
Gertrude;</hi> deſire F. <hi>Sweet</hi> if it be poſſible to get it for
vs, and ſend it to <hi>Rome,</hi> or elſe to <hi>Lovaine</hi> or
<hi>Tournay.</hi> There are the <hi>Hiſtories of</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                        <hi>Columban,</hi>
S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                        <hi>Rumuld,</hi> and <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Furſius,</hi> which his <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi>
hath given order ſhall be tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> for the good
and benefit of the lay-<hi>Catholicks.</hi> I beleeue the <hi>Hereticks</hi>
droope and begin to hold downe their heads of late<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> tis not poſſible
they ſhould hold vp long, either in <hi>England, France,</hi> or
<hi>Germany,</hi> they haue loſt their plumes. Let me know what the old
<hi>Blocke</hi> ſaith; you know my meaning. Send vs over if you can ſix or
ten young Schollers to <hi>Rome,</hi> Let not D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Kelliſon</hi> admit any
more at <hi>Doway,</hi> till there be ſupplie made here. There was one M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        <hi>Harelcot</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman here of late, and is
travailed hence to the <hi>Holy-Land,</hi> he had Letters of commendation from
F. <hi>Fiſher.</hi> Write to vs as oft as you can hereafter, that wee
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3205:18"/>may heare how things ſucceed. Haue among you <hi>Cor vnum
&amp; animam vnam.</hi> And ſo praying to our <hi>Lady</hi> and <hi>All
Saints</hi> for the extirpatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Hereſie</hi> among you, with
commendations to my kindred, you know whom I loue beſt, not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting
<hi>G. Smith,</hi> who will wonder he had no Letter from me. I Reſt.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your brother in <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                           <hi>H.
Floud.</hi>
                        </signed> 
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Rome.</hi>
                           <date>March 27. 1623.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <div type="comment">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:3205:19"/>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A ſhort Comment vpon Maſter <hi>Flouds</hi> long
Letter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ndorſed, <hi>To Father Colleton Archdeacon of London</hi>]
To another Letter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, Father <hi>Colleton</hi> hath ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
himſelfe, <hi>Vicarius generalis orien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis Angliae, Vicar generall of the
Eaſt of England</hi> Promotion comes very faſt on him. For I heare moreover
that of late, he is made <hi>Deane</hi> of <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon;</hi> which I doe not
ſee by what diſpenſation he can hold, being ſo farre remote as
<hi>London</hi> is from <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> yet I will try whether I can
likewiſe get him a facultie to be <hi>Deane</hi> of
<hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>His Holines hath made three new Biſhops.</hi>] It is
queſtioned whether his <hi>Holines</hi> be a <hi>Biſhop</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
for that ſince <hi>Gregory</hi> the thirteenth, there hath beene no true
<hi>Pope:</hi> but all that haue ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him haue beene meere Intruders
into the <hi>Papacy. vide.</hi> A Booke Intituled, <hi>The New man,</hi>
tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>William Craſhaw,</hi> Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelor
in Divinitie, according to the Latine Copie ſent from <hi>Rome</hi> into
<hi>England,</hi> Printed 1622.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:3205:19"/>
                     <hi>Dr</hi> 
                     <hi>Biſhop is Biſhop of
Chalcedon and comes ſhortly into England.</hi>] I will beleeue him another
time. For according to his promiſe true it is, that the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of
<hi>Chalcedon</hi> is come into <hi>England,</hi> and hath laid about him
<hi>in Pontificalibus,</hi> having <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed</hi> many, and
<hi>ordained</hi> ſome. When I was their childe, they would haue had mee
receiue Confirmation from him. Tis ſtrange I refuſd it, when ſo many
gaping, gazing gulls flockt after him (as after a <hi>Lord</hi> at
<hi>Whitſon</hi>) with deſire to kiſſe but the very ground where he had
ſtood.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aſperges me Domine</hi> ſaith the
Holy mightie man, <hi>Mundati e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis</hi> ſaith his Chaplaine M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        <hi>Ouerton.</hi>
                     </note>Oh bleſſed they that were aſperged but with the
leaſt drop of his thrice hallowed <hi>Holy water. Mundati ſunt,</hi> they
were purged from all ſinne. But what ſhall I ſay of thoſe who had the
liuery and hanſell of his ſacred <hi>Crozier-ſtaffe,</hi> when his
Lordſhip lorded it with his taper-bearers of each ſide, and one with a
Cenſor burning Incenſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him? Oh ſurely thoſe that had this
Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction (as <hi>Fr. Leech</hi> ſaid vpon another occaſion) <hi>Peccare
non poſsint ſi maximé velint,</hi> twas almoſt impoſſible for
them to commit any more ſinne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dr</hi> 
                     <hi>Bath and F. Iohn Roch are made Biſhops, the
one of Gortyna, the other of Cydonea, and are to be ſent into Ireland.</hi>]
Were I in <hi>Ireland</hi> and there wanted a <hi>Biſhops</hi>
Benediction or Confirmation, I might I thinke run over a great deale of ground,
and leaue many a merry old Towne behinde me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhould finde the
ſeverall Seas of theſe two new-ſtampt <hi>Biſhops;</hi> but caſting
mine eyes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Globe of the whole earth, I find that <hi>Gortyna</hi> and
<hi>Cydonea</hi> are two renowned Cities of the Ile of<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3205:20"/>
                     <hi>Creete</hi> or <hi>Candy,</hi> which Iland (as <hi>Strabo</hi>
writeth) is compaſſed with the <hi>Aegean, Affrican, Egilan,</hi> and
<hi>Cytheran</hi> Seas. So that by the next packet that comes from
<hi>Rome</hi> to the <hi>Popes</hi> Councell in <hi>Ireland,</hi> I deſire to
be reſolved whether <hi>per mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem</hi> or elſe <hi>per lapſum</hi>
theſe two new <hi>Biſhops</hi> came to their Seas. Secondly, I would be
ſatisfied concerning the largenes of thoſe two Dioceſſes
<hi>Gortyna</hi> and <hi>Cydonea;</hi> and how long the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of
<hi>Ireland</hi> (divided from the Continent of <hi>Creete</hi> by a great many
lakes and gulfes) hath beene within their precints. Thirdly I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know
what revennewes are annexed or appendant to thoſe ſaid
<hi>Biſhoprickes,</hi> that the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> chuſe rather to be
commorant at their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner houſes in <hi>Ireland,</hi> than at their ancient
Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at home.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If matters ſucceed well, there will be other new
Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and an Arch-biſhop ſent over.</hi>] They muſt waite for
another winde before they croſſe the Seas. Tis a dangerous ſtorme; many
of their Mates are like to ſuffer ſhip-wracke. But I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue they make
account that their <hi>Hierarchy</hi> ſhall blow away ours.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Our Colledge-money from the Catholickes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land comes
in ſlowly.</hi>] I perceiue according to the old Proverb, <hi>The Engliſh
Catholickes are ſtill the Popes Aſſes.</hi> But he is beholding to his
<hi>Ianizaries</hi> the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> who will whip them ſoundly if
they beare not their accuſtomed loads. Yet I heare that in the Northerne
parts, their Mules backes are almoſt burſten with over-riding.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:3205:20"/>
                     <hi>There is three hundred pounds to
receiue behinde</hi>] It were a fit <hi>Quere</hi> what they haue received,
ſo many of their Cuſtomers being obſerved of late to be turned
Bankrupts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wright ſend an hundred pounds from his
ſtocke.</hi>] It were good grafting vpon this ſtocke that beares ſo
fruitfull branches.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There are the Hiſtories of</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Columban, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muld, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Furſius, <hi>which his Holines hath given order to be
tranſlated</hi> &amp;c.] I warrant you there be good huskes in this trough to
feed <hi>Roman Catholicke Piggs</hi> of devouring beliefe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Catholicks droop, they cannot hold vp long,</hi>
&amp;c.] See how they haue caſt the dye to make vs loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers and
Bankrupts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let me know what the old Blocke ſaith.</hi>] Wee are
ſuch Block-heads that we doe not yet vnderſtand who this Blocke is. The
Ieſuites <hi>Cabala</hi> muſt helpe vs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Praying for the extirpation of hereſie.</hi>]
Extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? The zeale of this Prayer may kindle an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion of Gun-powder,
if need be.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="comment">
                  <head>The Letter ſubſcribed by <hi>H. Floud.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Haue heard there are three <hi>Flouds,</hi> notorious
proiecting proditorious <hi>Ieſuites</hi> beyond the Seas, all of them well
ſtudied in <hi>Machiauell.</hi> One of them cauſed the <hi>Ieſuites</hi>
at <hi>Liſbon</hi> to ſpend a great deale of money vpon Powder on a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3205:21"/>Feſtivall day a little before the
<hi>Powder-Treaſon</hi> in <hi>England</hi> ſhould haue beene effected,
thereby to make experience of the force thereof. And alſo perſwaded one
<hi>Iohn How</hi> (a Merchant whom he had perverted) and divers other
<hi>Catholickes</hi> to goe over into <hi>England,</hi> and to expect their
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption there (as he called it) a while. He is much honoured by the
<hi>State-Papists</hi> of this Kingdome. Some I haue heard giue a large
teſtimony of his Wiſedome and Worth. I beleeue it is he that was the Father
of this peſtilent LETTER.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:3205:21"/>
               <head>¶ A Letter ſent from one M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>VVorthington</hi> a
Prieſt, to a kinſman of his living in <hi>Lancaſhire.</hi>
               </head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The Coppie of this Letter I haue from
<hi>Worthingtons</hi> friend, who will iuſtifie the truth of
it.</note>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orthy and well-beloued Coſen, you fhall pleaſe to vnderſtand,
that at my late being at <hi>Tholouſe</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued your Letter, and
returned an anſwer therevnto againe, though (as I heare) it never came to
your hands. Since haue I beene at <hi>Roan,</hi> where I met with another
Letter of yours, which I had not time to anſwer from thence, neither would
the anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it there haue beene convenient. Since am I come to
<hi>Hage</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> where I can ſcarſe endure to heare the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3205:22"/>laviſh and vile ſpeeches which a ſort of baſe
vnbridled people daily diſgorge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Maieſtie of the <hi>King of
Spaine.</hi> For ſingularity among the people I haue noted, that they are
generally ſo bred vp to the <hi>Bible,</hi> that almoſt every Cobler is a
Dutch Doctour of Divinitie, and by inward illumination of ſpirit,
vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth the Scripture as well as he that wrote it. Thoſe of
<hi>Holland</hi> and the adia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent parts terme themſelues of the <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
Provinces;</hi> but never people in this world liued in a more diſvnited
vnitie; ſo great a confuſion hath this freedome brought among them of every
Idiots babling out of the <hi>Bible.</hi> There are not more different
languages at the Tower of <hi>Babel,</hi> then there are different beliefes in
<hi>Holland.</hi> But I leaue them to their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and inward
illuminations, bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from <hi>Martin Luther</hi> the
<hi>New-Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion-maker</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> and deſire you let me heare
ſo ſoone as may be what newes in <hi>England,</hi> whether the
<hi>Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> be yet come forth for <hi>Toleration,</hi> that we may
make vs merry at home in our <pb n="39" facs="tcp:3205:22"/>Kingdome without controule. I
was told by one M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Hinſlow</hi> ſome two or three dayes ſince, that
there is three or foure Churches building in <hi>London</hi> for
<hi>Catholickes,</hi> and that the King hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the <hi>Biſhop</hi>
of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> to Preach at <hi>Pauls-Croſſe,</hi> and that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        <hi>Fiſher</hi> hath Preached before his Maieſtie twiſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie. If
this be true I will be with you within this moneth. I heare the <hi>Prince</hi>
was married vpon <hi>Eaſter</hi> day laſt, a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman told me who was
then at <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid.</hi> I could acquaint you with all the ſolemnitie, but
that I know you heare the newes in <hi>England</hi> as ſoone as it is with
vs. F. <hi>Maſon</hi> is lately dead, and much lamented at <hi>Bruxells.</hi>
I was in good hope my ſiſter <hi>Ioan</hi> would haue come over to mee
before this time. I ſpake to the <hi>Lady Abbeſſe</hi> for her, who hath
promiſed ſhee ſhall be preſently admitted, and will accept of
eightſcore pounds. I pray you to pay ten pounds for me to my Coſen
<hi>Maxfield</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> which I ſent vnto him for, and I haue
received it. I wiſh his brother <hi>Henry</hi> and<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3205:23"/>we
could agree as well in minde and iudgement, as we doe in ancient amity. I could
write ſome other newes hence, but for reaſons I ſpare, till I be departed
hence, and then I ſhall make you laugh. For this time in haſt I leaue you
to God, and in all kinde affection I take of you my leaue, deſiring you to
remember me to all thoſe to whom in dutie and loue I am bounden, I need not
name them all, but reſt</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your loving kinſman <hi>I.
Worthington.</hi>
                        </signed> 
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Hage,</hi>
                           <date>this 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May.</hi>
1623.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <div type="comment">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:3205:23"/>
                  <head>The Comment.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S for the former part of his Letter which concerneth the
<hi>Hollanders,</hi> they are of age to anſwer for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What newes in England, whether the Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be yet
come forth for Toleration.</hi>] The hope of a <hi>Toleration</hi> is the Wine
that ſeaſons all their mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Feaſts; but I hope their Wine is turnd to
Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by another <hi>Proclamation,</hi> though ſome (I heare) make but a
ieſt of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Three or foure Churches building in London for
Catholickes.</hi>] <hi>Riſum teneatis amici?</hi> Belike they are like
thoſe Churches <hi>builded vpon the ſand,</hi> a floud came and waſhd
them away. I wonder to which of their new Canonizd rubricall Saints thoſe new
Churches muſt be dedicated: Oh I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Nicholas Nemo,</hi>
and the Pariſh where they ſtand is <hi>Nullibi</hi> in the
<hi>Metropolis</hi> of <hi>Eutopia.</hi> Goe aske S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Thomas Moore</hi> on
which end of thoſe Churches the Weather-cocke ſhall ſtand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The King hath appointed the Biſhop of Chalcedon to
Preach at Pauls-Croſſe.</hi>] Yes very true, and his Text muſt be
<hi>Act.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Epiſcopatum eius alter ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiat. His Biſhopricke
let another take.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Fiſher hath Preached before his Maieſtie twice
alreadie.</hi>] As true as ſteele. And there to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of his Auditory
he told his owne heroicall<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3205:24"/>Acts in producing Actors from
Heaven and <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatery,</hi> for the <hi>Nunnizing</hi> of <hi>Mary
Wiltſhire, Mary Boucher,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
                     <hi>Francis Peard,</hi> and others his
ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly children.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I heare the Prince was married vpon Eaſter day.</hi>]
True and truſty newes. The Capons are not yet fed that ſhould be eaten at
that Feaſt, and yet the <hi>Epithilamium</hi> or <hi>Marriage-Song</hi> is
made by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Pateſon</hi> in the dedication to the Booke cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<hi>The image of both Churches.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Lady Abbeſſe will accept of eight ſcore
pounds.</hi>] I verily beleeue it and more money if ſhee could get it. A good
Broker for Dowries; but thoſe Dowries ſuck a great deale of money out of
<hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I ſhall make you laugh.</hi>] Good ſport belike. In
the meane time we laugh at you (good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Worthington</hi>) for your
newes of <hi>non ens;</hi> and that you build Churches and Caſtles in the
ayre.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:3205:24"/>
               <head>¶ A Letter ſent from the ſaid <hi>J.
VVorthington</hi> to his Vnckle in <hi>London,</hi> a <hi>Seminary
Prieſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Moſt loving <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkle,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know you take it very vnkindly that I wrote not vnto you by
the laſt packet; but the reaſon was becauſe I intended to haue come over
within a weeke fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, had not D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Kelliſon</hi> hindred me. Let mee
intreat you to provide ſome good houſe where I may be entertained in
<hi>London</hi> at. <hi>Mid-ſummer,</hi> when I intend to ſee
<hi>England.</hi> Wee vnderſtand there is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie enough now, every man
with<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3205:25"/>you may vſe his Conſcience. My Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen
<hi>Melling</hi> wrote vnto me that they ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to purchaſe all the Churches
in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> if this world laſt long. The heaven hath beene long
full with our cryes, the world with our afflictions, <hi>Sed tandem miſerendi
tempus, exultandi dies. Purſuivants,</hi> men infamous, who at their
pleaſures inriched themſelues with the ſpoyle of our goods, I heare that
now they ſneake vp and downe, and the onely preferment any of them can
attaine vnto, is to keepe a <hi>Tobacco-ſhop.</hi> Wee ſhall no more I hope
be made a <hi>Spectacle</hi> to the <hi>World, and to Angels, and to men.</hi>
But <hi>Niſi praecedit pugna, non ſuccedit victoria,</hi> ſayth S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                        <hi>Cyprian.</hi> It is a comfort that the caſe is ſo altered. <hi>Interim
Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus.</hi> I was lately at the <hi>Hage</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> where
I found but ſeaven Religions in one Familie; the man of the houſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of
one Religion, the wife of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the children and ſervants of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. The
high powerfull <hi>Lords</hi> the <hi>States</hi> keepe a great toyle there,
though<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3205:25"/>the beſt of them were but the ſonne of a
<hi>Beere-Brewer</hi> or <hi>Basket-Maker.</hi> I ſaw there King
<hi>Iames</hi> his daughter and her Worſhipfull Husband, whoſe high
aſpiring thoughts are now low enough, even as low as that mud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die Countrey is
beneath any ſound earth. Their dwellings are fitter to be a habitation for
fiſhes than for men. I got an Ague there which I was afraid I ſhould not
ſo ſoone haue ſhaken off. I would entreat you Vnckle to ſend me over to
<hi>Doway</hi> fiue pounds, to fit mee with ſome neceſſaries againſt my
Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: And I haue written to my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen <hi>Maxfield</hi> to ſend mee
fiue more. I haue Printed a Booke which I will bring over with mee, I am ſure
that will helpe mee with money enough in <hi>England.</hi> I was at
<hi>Anwerpe</hi> where I bought a Box of <hi>hallowed Rings,</hi> which I value
at a great rate, ſo that I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to pay my debts to your ſelfe and
others my good friends when I haue beene a while in <hi>England.</hi> Wiſh my
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3205:26"/>Coſen <hi>Maxfield</hi> to ſhew you his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. I
remember my dutie vnto you, and ſo reſt</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your loving Nephew <hi>I.
Worthington.</hi>
                        </signed> 
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Duac.</hi>
                           <date>
                              <hi>May</hi> 20. 1623.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <div type="comment">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:3205:26"/>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Comment.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et mee intreat you to provide ſome good houſe where
I may be intertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi>] His harbinger hath provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him a houſe in
<hi>Holborne,</hi> one of thoſe that ſtand in the next way to
<hi>Tyburne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My coſen</hi> Melling <hi>wrote, that they hoped (if
this world laſt long) to purchaſe all the Churches in Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſhire.</hi>]
Wee thanke your coſen <hi>Melling</hi> for tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a long laſting
world; But as for <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> I can giue by my abode in it, ſome
little account of it, and of their acquaintances ſwelling into thouſands,
yet I hope they ſhall never purchaſe Church there, though they haue
purchaſed and invaded too many houſes and families.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Purſuivants</hi> &amp;c.] Doe they now ſcorne the
Officers of Iuſtice and Religion amongſt vs? If hereafter thoſe Pipes
that haue for a time bin put vp in a bag ſhall be plaid on againe, let not
thoſe take it in ſnuffe who haue now made no more of our Lawes made
againſt them then of a vaniſhing euaporated whiffe of <hi>Tobacco.</hi> And
as for the <hi>Purſuivants,</hi> they would haue this libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling knaue to
know, that the worſt of them hath meanes to maintaine himſelfe without
being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to any <hi>Popiſh</hi> Pedlarly Prieſt whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:3205:27"/>
                     <hi>Interim Germanicus.</hi>] Cunningly
ſpoken. I thinke he alludes to the <hi>Interim</hi> in the time of
<hi>Charles</hi> the fift, and would imply that they haue in <hi>England</hi> a
midling proviſionall ſect of <hi>Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, Temporizing Romaniſts,</hi>
who can conforme to the times, in hope they ſhall be otherwiſe fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer bent
for their ends. Many here are that tread vpon <hi>Roman</hi> earth, though
<hi>Engliſh ground.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Beere-brewer or Basket-maker.</hi>] Hee had this ieſt
out of <hi>Robert Parſons,</hi> the brazen-fac'd libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<hi>Ieſuite</hi> his bookes. But yet thoſe <hi>Brewers</hi> he ſpeakes of
haue made drinke ſo ſtrong that it hath oft beene huffecap to their
enemies. And their Baskets haue beene ſo ſtuft with earth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their
rampiers, that the greateſt Ordnance of the enemy could not demoliſh them
at <hi>Bergen vp-Zone.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whoſe high aſpiring hopes,</hi> &amp;c.] God may
pleaſe to giue them a time to repaire their decayes, which they patiently
expect. But it may be ſome triall of their patience, to haue their loſſes
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubled by ſtormes from that faction whoſe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters haue procured
and continued thoſe da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I got an Ague there.</hi>] By feeling your purſe I find
you haue <hi>febrem peſtilentem,</hi> at leaſt a malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant fever; your
bloud and ſpirits being poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a callenture gotten or
increaſed by the bad ayre vpon the bankes of <hi>Tyber.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I haue printed a little Bocke.</hi>] No doubt it is a
goodly worke made by this fiue pound man. Some bungling botcherly bundle of
miracula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3205:27"/>Saints piping new. Let M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Henry
Barber</hi> of <hi>Holborne</hi> haue the vttering and diſperſing of it,
who met me within theſe few daies and challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged mee for putting him into my
<hi>Catalogue</hi> of <hi>Popiſh Booke-ſellers,</hi> and ſaid he had
little reaſon to haue gone in among them, for that he had beene in priſon
for it heretofore. Or if <hi>Henry Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> be by this meanes too infamous,
I commend you M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Worthington</hi> to another Trader, one M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                     <hi>Vdall</hi> of <hi>Gunpowder-Alley,</hi> who was very angry that in my
Catalogue I put him downe plaine <hi>Vdall</hi> without an M. at his
girdle.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Money inough.</hi>] Pray marke how theſe chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Mates
make a prey of their credulous Laick Diſciples. They count it no ſmall part
of their reuennew the ſummes which they ſqueiſe by dropping idle pocket
Pamphlets which they ſell at an high Market and vnreaſonable rates, as
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue ſhewed in divers particulars. I doubt whether they haue wit
inough that vpon theſe occaſions furniſh them with moneys inough.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A boxe of hollowed rings, which I value at a great
rate.</hi>] Doth he make them Hogs whom he thus ringeth, or rather wringeth by
extracting good ſilver from men &amp; women paſt Non-age, though not Dotage
for ſuch rattle-baby toyes? Oh Trumpery! Is this zeale and Chriſtian
Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Why doe we laugh at the barbarous <hi>Indians</hi> for imparting to
vs their richeſt commodities in exchange for glaſſe, beads, peny
whittles, copper rings, &amp;c? But the <hi>Popes Benediction,</hi> or any the
leaſt touch of Sainting Miracle-monging fiction<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3205:28"/>is able to
infuſe the higheſt worth into the baſeſt baggagely New-nothing to hang
vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſleeue of admiring adoring ghoſtly Children of the
<hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites.</hi> How doth his <hi>Holines</hi> exorciſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure
<hi>Beads</hi> of wood, of ſtone, of Corall, and of all other ſtuffe,
making beſotted Ignaro's beleeue they haue great power againſt ſinne, the
Devill, and Hell; whereas alas all is but cheating, and to gull them of their
money. (<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:3205:28"/>
               <head>The Coppie of a Letter Indorſed as followeth.</head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>Au Treſreverend Pere le Pere <hi>Berville,</hi> Generall
des Peres de la Congregation de L'oratoire en <hi>France</hi> a
<hi>Paris.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>REverendiſſime Pater,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eeſt nobis hoc tempore homo prudens, diligens, &amp;
conſtans, qui negotia Epiſcopi noſtri, &amp; Cleri in Curiâ
Romanâ tractet: Habetis in veſtra Congregatione R. P. <hi>Thomam
Rant</hi> Anglum, qui Italicé loquitur, &amp; Romae aliquando verſatus
cum laude eſt, &amp; in Anglia antequam Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem veſtram
ingrediebatur cauſis agendis diu, multum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſtuduit. Hunc idoneu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
reputamus, cui ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotia noſtra co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittamus. Rogamus ita<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
Reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſsimam Paternitatem veſtram vt hunc virum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis concedat, vel ad
tempus ſaltem commo let, ne R<hi rend="sup">mi</hi> Epiſcopi et noſtrae cauſae oportuno
praeſidio in ea altiſsima Curia diſtitutae ſint Veſtrae
Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis proprium eſſe inaudiuimus viros pios et pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3205:29"/>Epiſcopis concedere: quapropter ſummis preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus
obſecramus, ne hanc gratiam denegetis Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nario noſtro veſtri
amantiſsimo, qui hoc etiam a Paternitate veſtra Reverendiſsima antea
petiit. Quo quidem beneficio nos omnes ſibi &amp; Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioni ſuae
ſummopere devinciet. Deus Reuerendiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam Paternitatem veſtram
diutiſsimé ſeruet inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumen.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Reverendiſſimae Paternita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis veſtrae
obſervantiſſimi,
<list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Ioannes Colletonus</hi> Vicarius generalis
orientalis Angliae.</item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Richardus Smitheus</hi> 
                                 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icarius generalis in
partibus Auſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus Angliae.</item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Richardus Broughtonus</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carius generalis
Septentriona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis partis Angliae.</item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Edwardus Bennettus</hi> Vicarius generalis in
partibus Occiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talibus Angliae.</item>
                           </list>
                        </signed> 
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Londini</hi>
                           <date>24. <hi>Septembris Anno Domini</hi>
1623.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <div type="translation">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:3205:29"/>
                  <head>The former Letter in <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Indorſed</head>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <head>To the moſt reverend Father the Father
<hi>Beruille,</hi> Generall of the Fathers of the Congregation of the Oratory
in <hi>France,</hi> deliver this in <hi>Paris.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Most reverend Father,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">He meanes the late new caſt Biſhop of
<hi>Chalcedon.</hi>
                           </note>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE want at this preſent a wiſe, diligent, and
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant man, who may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch the buſineſſes of our
<hi>Biſhop</hi> and Clergie in the Roman Court. You haue in your Congregation
a reverend Father, one <hi>Thomas Rant</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, who
ſpeakes <hi>Italian</hi> and hath beene to his commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſometime
imployed at <hi>Rome;</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he was much and long imployed in
<hi>England</hi> in ſoliciting of buſineſſes, before his admiſſion
to your Congregation. This man wee thinke fit to truſt with our
affayres.<note place="margin">Their affayres are Faires to purchaſe
mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</note> And therefore, we beſeech<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3205:30"/>your moſt
reverend Father-hood that you would grant vs this man, or at leaſt lend him
vs for a time, leaſt the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend <hi>Biſhops</hi> affaires &amp;
ours ſhould be deſtitute of Protection, as occaſion may ſerue in that
moſt high Court. We haue heard that it is proper to your Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to
affoord pious &amp; prudent men vnto <hi>Biſhops.</hi> Wherefore wee
earneſtly intreat you, that you would not deny our <hi>Ordinary</hi> this
favour, who doth fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently loue you, and hath heretofore requeſted thus much
from your moſt reverend Father-hood. By which bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit your Father-hood
ſhall much oblige vs all to your ſelfe and your Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. God long
preſerue your moſt reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father-hood in proſperitie.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your moſt reverend Father-hoods much bounden,

<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Iohn Colleton</hi> Vicar generall of the Eaſt
parts of <hi>England.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Richard Smith</hi> Vicar generall of the South
parts of <hi>England.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Richard Broughton</hi> Vicar generall of the
North parts of <hi>England.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Edward Bennet</hi> Vicar generall of the Weſt
parts of <hi>England.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed> 
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>London</hi>
                              <date>24 of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember.</hi>
1623.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
               <div type="comment">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:3205:30"/>
                  <head>The Comment.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Oore <hi>England</hi> you finde quartered without
<hi>iudgement,</hi> by this dominee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Quaternion</hi> of Popiſh
popular <hi>Quarter-maſters.</hi> An admirable new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erected intruded
<hi>Hierarchy.</hi> Our <hi>Lord Biſhops</hi> had need looke to their
Rochets. For I heare of a ſtrange imaginary ſcambling after the reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes
of their Church-livings. Great hopes there is of purchaſing Churches, &amp;
great newes of ſending over more new Biſhops. The nimble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>footed
Meſſengers deligated from the <hi>Popes Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines,</hi> may intrude where
they liſt and obtrude what they pleaſe (it ſhould ſeeme) without
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint or reproofe. Alas great <hi>Roman Idoll-Gull,</hi> there is none
of our <hi>Biſhops</hi> that feare your leaden Bull. As for your
<hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Chalcedon, Gortyna,</hi> and <hi>Cydonea,</hi> who
haue their authoritie ſo braue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſigned <hi>ſub annulo
Piſcatoris,</hi> I deſire them to tarry where their land lyes that may
maintaine them <hi>in Pontificalibus.</hi> The truth is, in <hi>England</hi> we
haue as yet no emptie Palace worthy to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine them except it be the
<hi>Gate-houſe</hi> at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> or the <hi>Stone
houſe</hi> at <hi>New-gate,</hi> where they ſhall be pompouſly
attended.</p>
                  <p>Is it not inough that the <hi>little Foxes</hi> of
<hi>Rome</hi> eate vp our Grapes, but other <hi>wild Boares</hi> muſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3205:31"/>muſt enter into our <hi>Vineyard?</hi> The Lord hath yet
a <hi>hooke for their noſtrils and a bridle for their lips.</hi> Let
<hi>Abaddon</hi> the <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>Locusts,</hi> that
<hi>Romiſh</hi> vſurper raue and braue, ſeeking to inlarge his
Territories from Eaſt to Weſt, or as far as he lift, claiming
<hi>Hyperbolicall</hi> power to beare through <hi>Diabolicall</hi> drifts; It
makes no matter; our <hi>Ioſiah</hi> (whoſe name ſhall ever remaine vpon
record in the <hi>Kalender</hi> of the iuſt) hath taken away all
ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations of iniquitie, all intruding Iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that might ſtreame
hither from the Well of <hi>Rome;</hi> having in himſelfe
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, an inbred power, limited onely
with iuſtice and equitie; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
abſolute dominion and vniverſall command; and yet
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> alſo, ſubiection to none but
God onely. And who (but the <hi>Pope</hi> and his adherents) doubteth, but that
the limmes and branches of his authoritie are extended over all perſons and
in all cauſes as well <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> as <hi>Civilli</hi> His
power profeſſion and facultie is immediate and next vnto God, held from him
<hi>in Capite,</hi> not derived from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath: he is not one of thoſe Princes
of whom <hi>Blondus</hi> ſpeaketh, that ſhould honor and worſhip the Pope
as God; he kiſſeth not the hands and feet of his <hi>Holines,</hi> but is
<hi>architectonicall,</hi> ſupreame and commander of all other functions and
voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Blond. Iuſt. Roma. lib.</hi> 3.
<hi>Bertrandus.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:3205:31"/>
               <head>¶ The Coppy of a Letter ſent from <hi>P. Rowe</hi> a
<hi>Romiſh Prieſt,</hi> to his brother <hi>William Rowe</hi> in
ENGLAND.</head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Loving Brother,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit according to S. <hi>Bernards</hi> ſaying,
<hi>Efficacior lingua quam li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera:</hi> The tongue is of greater efficacy then
the Penne, And ſo I could wiſh rather to inlarge my ſelfe vnto you by
word then by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, (my occaſion of writing vnto you at this time being
very ſerious) yet ſith according to the old Proverb, Gainſt
neceſſitie there is no law, I will plead my cauſe by this mute Advocate
of my minde.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Thoſe that are of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Orders vow
obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their Superiours, who may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them to run to any Angle of
the world, to the <hi>Indies.</hi>
                        </note>So it is that I haue received command
from our Superior to travell to the Citie of <hi>Seleucia</hi> within the
Province of <hi>Iſauria,</hi>
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:3205:32"/>a place I know not where,
&amp; ſo I know not whether euer I ſhall ſee <hi>England</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. I
will delay my Iourney eight weekes longer, and would intreat you (as you
reſpect me) to ſend me over be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my going the thirtie pounds you owe me.
Though I told you I would forbeare it a yeare longer, yet now I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe it,
neither would you I hope deſire it, conſidering my caſe. I had come this
Sommer into <hi>England,</hi> but that the <hi>Superior</hi> of our Order is
thus pleaſed to put a tricke vpon me, the burthen whereof I muſt patiently
vnder-goe. I haue deſerved better I am ſure, then to be ſo foyſted off
and driven God knows where. I wrote vnto you a fortnight ſince by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        <hi>Herbart,</hi> deſiring you to ſend me a dozen yards of good
broad-cloth, of a fine new mixt colour for a friend of mine. Wee every day
expect to heare from you and to receiue it. The money that is in my brother
<hi>Iames</hi> hands I freely forgiue him, for I know he needs it.
<note place="margin">The Popes pardons you find are hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
purchaſed.</note>I procured M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Shepheard</hi> an <hi>Indulgence,</hi>
but there is yet twelue pounds of the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3205:32"/>vnſent, I
harken ſtill when I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it. If he haue not yet taken order (as I
appointed him) for the payment of it in <hi>Anwerpe;</hi> I pray ſpeake to
him that he ſend it over with your money. I pray let there be no iarring
betwixt my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Robert</hi> and you: I haue written to him and charged
him deeply to behaue himſelfe ſoberly and lovingly toward you. Had I come
over as was intended, wee might haue had great comfort one of another. I envy
not the braue life which my fellow Prieſts in <hi>England</hi> now lead.
Remember me dearely to Maſter <hi>Browne,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Midleton,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        <hi>Iones,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Curley,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Bond,</hi> and whom elſe of my
acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance you meet withall, and let them know what is become of me. Tell
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Midleton</hi> that he looke well to my Bookes, and if I never
ſee him againe they are his. I deſire him to write to me ſo ſoone as he
can. Let me heare how the <hi>Catholicke Cauſe</hi> doth thriue of late. I
heare all is as we would haue it.<note place="margin"> Not ſo Sir, for you
would haue all turnd topſie turuye. Againe your new <hi>Hierarchy</hi> is not
yet eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.</note> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not write what I would at this time,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3205:33"/>but deferre it till I heare of another Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger. And
ſo deſiring you to pray for me I reſt</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your loving Brother, <hi>P. Rowe.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Liſle</hi>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Aprill</hi> 8. 1623.</date>
                        </dateline> 
                     </closer>
                     <postscript>
                        <p>The <hi>Hollanders</hi> haue had a late overthrow; and for
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Newes we haue none.</p>
                     </postscript>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <div type="comment">
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:3205:33"/>
                  <head>The Comment.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hoſe newes now which the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> the
Authors of the aforeſaid Letters intended ſhould be <hi>Occulté
dimiſſa</hi> privately conveyed to their true-hearted friends in
<hi>England,</hi> are by a wrong Meſſenger, <hi>Oculis &amp; auribus
ſubiecta infidelibus,</hi> miſcarried farre contrary to their hopes and
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation. It is eaſily collected from their ſaid Letters of what
ſpirit and temper they are, what marke they ſhoot at. I deſire the Reader
to make conſtruction of ſome things himſelfe. I haue by the meanes of
good friends come to the ſight of other Letters of theirs, all which ſavour
of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but rancour and malice againſt vs <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</hi> But
alas what are all their ſtout Invectiues, but ſo many guſts of wind to
drowne in diſgrace the ſhip of Chriſt? What are all their threats but
raging waues that batter her? What are their pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh and malicious
ſlanders, the fond abſurdities they foiſt vpon vs, but horrible
monſters? What all their brags and boaſts, but <hi>Syrens</hi> ſongs?
Such waues againſt Gods Church haue never wanted in any age, who by battering
her haue broken themſelues; yet will not the latter learne of the former, nor
feare their ends whoſe courſes they<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3205:34"/>follow, but with a
new rage of fury run to their ruine.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <div type="proclamation">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:3205:34"/>
               <head>A PROCLAMATION Concerning the Sale of <hi>Jndul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences</hi>
at the next <hi>Staple Faire</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> now neere at hand <hi>Anno
Domini</hi> 1625. Called the great yeare of <hi>Iubilee.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnknowne to the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neder ſort eſpecially of
thoſe who liue within the Circle of the Chriſtian Papalizing world, that
this preſent yeare of Grace 1624. is the Eeue or Vigill of the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>th iolly yeare of <hi>Iubilee,</hi>
beginning <hi>In die Natalis Domini prox.</hi> when the grand Mart of
<hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons &amp; Indulgences</hi> is to be ſet vp, and open ſhop thereof
to be kept in the Pope-holy merry old Citie of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Eeue of this great <hi>Staple Faire,</hi> it behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth
we who haue devoted my ſelfe in all ſervice to his <hi>Holines,</hi> to
exhort and adviſe all tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> to provide
themſelues with two things eſpecially, <hi>Sinnes inough,</hi> and <hi>Gold
inough.</hi> Sinnes inough, elſe there will be no<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3205:35"/>wounds
to cure. Gold inough, elſe there will be no cure for the wounds. The weakenes
and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our nature will be get the firſt, we need no ſpurre to
gallop downe that Hill. And the corruptions of the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> will
attract the other.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Depoſcuntur opes tanquam medicina malorum,</l>
                  <l>Exportantur opes irritamenta malorum.</l>
               </q>
               <p>In this great <hi>Faire</hi> I muſt tell you wee haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but honeſt and faire dealing, our trading being by way of compenſation in
equall bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance. <hi>Sinne</hi> you know is ſo heavie a thing that it
<hi>preſſeth a man downe into Hell.</hi> Nothing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is able to lift
a man vp from the downefall, but that which it ſelfe is moſt heavie.
Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy and Experience tell vs, that <hi>Auro nihil gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius,</hi> no
created matter in the world weighes heavier then gold. Nothing therefore hath
our hallowing holy Father the Pope thought fitter to put into his ſcales to
lift men out of <hi>Purgatory</hi> and mount them on high than maſſie
ſilver and gold. Whereof if thou come to our Stations at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſee
thou bring thy burthen and weight. <hi>Auro enim nihil r arius, nil charius,
nil ſuauius, nil gratius.</hi> Nothing at his <hi>Holines</hi> Market may be
ſold without gold. But bring that; and then as for <hi>Diſpenſations,
Abſolutions, Appellations, Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Inueſtitures,</hi> and ſuch
<hi>Intereſts</hi> as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth affoord, thou ſhalt
want none; So ſay the <hi>Negotiators</hi> of that <hi>Apoſtolicall
Sea.</hi> Oh<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3205:35"/>braue and beautifull <hi>Rome?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apoc. 18.</note>
                  <hi>The Merchants are waxen
rich with the aboundance of thy pleaſures. Vnde haberi poſsit
Indulgentiarum communicatio niſi ab hac ſede,</hi> ſaith
<hi>Bellarmine</hi> the great Bailif and Clerke of this Market? Who can forgiue
ſinnes but the <hi>Pope</hi> onely? His <hi>Pardons</hi> are that traffique
whereby the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (whereof his <hi>Holines</hi> is the Head)
keepeth her intimate correſpondency and participation with all her members,
tying thereby their conſciences by a ſecret and ſtrong obligation vnto
the Pontificall Seate.</p>
               <p>Doth any one thinke that they are ordinary trinkets and trifles
which are ſet to ſale in the <hi>Popes</hi> Market?<note place="margin">In
for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Papali.</note> Commodities
vendible at <hi>Stur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> or <hi>Bartholmew Faire?</hi> Fye younſter,
you are much deceived. Famous <hi>Babylon, the ſeauen hild Citie,</hi> Papall
<hi>Rome, Shee ſhall haue many that ſhall be Merchants vnto her of the
ſoules of men.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poc. 18. 13. Her <hi>Indulgences</hi> are a relaxation
of temporall paines inflicted vpon ſoules in <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</hi> And is it a
ſmall matter I pray you to eſcape the hot, fiery, flagrant, torrid,
ſulphurous ſmoake and flames of <hi>Purgatory?</hi> Oh no; It is written in
the Decrees,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Capit. quid in aliud diſtinct.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.</note> 
                  <hi>There is no earthly
paine or Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to be compared to the paines of Purgatory.</hi> And the
holy man that Angelicall Doctor <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Aquine</hi> ſaith,
<hi>That the paine of the fire of hell, and the fire of Purgatory is all one,
and that they differ no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, but that the one is but temporall and the
other eternall. Virgill</hi> ſet a partition of <hi>Iron</hi> and other
mettall betwixt thoſe two fires.<note place="margin">Aeneiad. lib. 6.</note>
Yet ſome<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3205:36"/>men be of opinion that the partition was but a
pale made of Wainſcot, which (becauſe it was of wood) was long agone burnt
away;
<note place="margin">Hell and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory both but one
Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chen.</note>ſo that now <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>Purgatory</hi> enter both
in at one hole and are both but one fire. There was a ſoule which had lyen
thirtie yeares in <hi>Purgatory</hi> (ſaith the Booke called <hi>Sermones
diſcipuli de Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore</hi>)<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sermones diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli de
tempore &amp; de ſanctis. ſerm.</hi> 160.</note> and at laſt there came
an Angell, who did bid the ſoule chuſe, whether it would tarry yet one
ſhort Winters day in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> or that it would returne into the
world againe, and there doe a marveilous hard penance, to wit, for one long
hundred yeares ſpace ſhould goe barefoot, and tread ſtill vpon ſharpe
iron nailes, eate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but browne bread, and drinke bitter gall
mingled with vinegar, and weare a cloth of Camels haire next the skinne, and a
ſtone vnder the head in place of a pillow. This ſoule did chuſe much
rather to doe all that ſame hard pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in earth, than to tarry one day
longer in <hi>Purgatory.</hi> Conſider now what a ſharpe, bitter, biting
ſauce <hi>Purgatory</hi> is, all the plagues &amp; pains whereof thou maiſt
eſcape if thou wilt but goe to the <hi>Faire</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and carry
ſome ſtore of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney with thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A prettie tale to tole Greiſt to the Popes
Mill.</note>In the territory of <hi>Apamea</hi> a towne of <hi>Syria,</hi>
there liued one <hi>German Moſſocus</hi> a man very rich and covetous. He
was adviſed by his friends in one of the yeares of <hi>Grace</hi> or
<hi>Iubilee</hi> to travell to <hi>Rome,</hi> there to be made a brother of the
<hi>Gild,</hi> and to partake of all the <hi>Indulgences, Remiſsions,
Priviledges, Liberties, Diſpenſations, Sacrifices, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictions,</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:3205:36"/>&amp;c. which his <hi>Holines</hi> is vſed to giue at
that time publickely: the ſaid <hi>German</hi> was ſo loth to part with his
money, and to be at any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence in trauelling to <hi>Rome,</hi> that he
choſe rather to looſe that great bleſſing offred him, then to vnlooſe
any of his worme-eaten rotten bags of ſiluer. Wherefore marke what followed.
His houſe was burnt downe to the ground, and his money periſhed therewith,
and him ſelfe narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at that time eſcaped the fire. And now his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
being all vaniſhed, he trauailed to <hi>Rome</hi> for <hi>Indulgence &amp;
Pardon</hi> for his ſinnes, where being arriued he entred into the Temple of
S. <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za,</hi> where there met him the Ghoſt of one
<hi>Iſoac</hi> a neighbour of his, who dyed ſome two yeares before, and
told him he had all that while beene in <hi>Purgatory;</hi> but now (quoth he)
by the helpe of the <hi>holy Maſſes, Mattenſes, Suffrages, Almeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds,
Pilgrimages,</hi> and other <hi>good workes of pietie and charitie</hi> had at
this time, I am delivered. Thoſe bitter paines that I haue indured (quoth the
Ghoſt) thou mighteſt haue eſcaped, but that thou didſt regard a little
dirt and duſt, that is thy money more then thy ſoule; thou haſt
eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of late one fire, the burning of thy body; but there is a worſe
fire the <hi>flames of Purgatory,</hi> which thou canſt not eſcape.
<hi>German Moſſocus</hi> herevpon much amazed, pined away and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a
weeke after dyed. And at the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant as he was departing out of the
world, he was heard pronounce theſe words; <hi>I ſee the Flame.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In the Booke called <hi>The proofe of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<hi>An.</hi> 1621. <hi>pag.</hi> 84. 85.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:3205:37"/>Againe, one <hi>Hernandes Garcia,</hi> Earle
of <hi>Caſtile</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> who warred much with
<hi>Almancor</hi> of <hi>Corduba</hi> King of the <hi>Moores,</hi> being to
fight a great battaile againſt his ſaid Adverſary, was deſirous afore
his going into the field to get our <hi>holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> the <hi>Popes
Benediction,</hi> not doubting but by meanes thereof he ſhould haue the more
proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſucceſſe. And ſo with haſt to <hi>Rome</hi> he went,
where being arrived he viſited his <hi>Holines,</hi> who did
<hi>Bleſſe</hi> him and thereby aſſured him of victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. At the ſame
time he obtained from his <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> a ſpeciall pardon and plenary
<hi>Indulgence</hi> for all his ſinnes; and then ſalied vpon the
<hi>Moores.</hi> In the conflict the <hi>Moores</hi> were chaſed, and
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably diſcomfited. Great cauſe here was for <hi>Hernandes</hi> to
praiſe God for the grace he received from his <hi>Holines,</hi> finding that
good iſſue in his aforeſaid affaires. But he became moſt ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
and did at a certaine time ſcoffe at the <hi>Popes Indulgences,</hi> no whit
regarding the ineſtimable weight thereof. But marke his reward: he was
preſently ſtricken <hi>lame</hi> and <hi>blinde.</hi> And after that there
appeared vnto him many thouſand ſoules, who ſaid they came out of
<hi>Purgatory,</hi> and did ſtriue amongſt themſelues who ſhould gaine
of his <hi>Holines</hi> that <hi>Pardon</hi> which had beene given to this
ſaid <hi>Hernand Garcia,</hi> and by him wretch not eſteemed.
<note place="margin">Belike it was Holiday with them that day: For
learned M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Stevens</hi> writeth that vpon any Saints day The ſoules in
<hi>Purgatory</hi> are at reſt.</note> This ſaid <hi>viſion</hi> brought
him to a remembrance of his impietie, &amp; a ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the
infinite myſtery of the <hi>Popes In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence,</hi> which is perfectly
auaileable to purge a man from his ſinnes, and to free him from the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3205:37"/>ſcorching paines of <hi>Purgatory.</hi> So that after, he
repented him of his former evill, and ſtill ſued vnto the <hi>Pope</hi> to
be againe mercifull vnto him. And after the performance of great
<hi>penance</hi> he was againe pardoned by his <hi>Holines.</hi> Which par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
was no ſooner granted, but he had his ſight reſtored him, and the perfect
vſe of his limmes as he had before. Witneſſe the Author of the Booke
before Cited, called <hi>The Proofe of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</hi> pag. 71. 72. <hi>Et
ſequ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here are too tales able to ſtop the mouth of the moſt
obſtinate Hereticke in the world, who ſhall be bold to ſay the <hi>Popes
Indulgences</hi> are but pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purſe traſh and trumpery: Oh yes note the
pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments of the contemners of them: marke their extraordinary operation,
farre beyond any quack-ſalving Empericks pill or potion. A man blinde and
lame you haue heard reſtored to his limmes and ſight by the holy
<hi>Fathers</hi> onely <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and <hi>Indulgence.</hi> And but that
one of his <hi>Holines Canonicall Authors</hi> told mee of it, I ſhould haue
ſworne it had beene a lye in a bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get. For my owne part I now know what to
thinke, beleeue it elſe who will.</p>
               <p>Yet it may be; as <hi>Aeſop</hi> deviſed all his
<hi>Fables</hi> for the <hi>Morals</hi> ſake: So the Popiſh Legendarians
inuent their tales to make a good morall vſe of them onely, for the wealth
and reputation of the <hi>Pope</hi> and his Clergie. <hi>Purgatory,
Pardons,</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences,</hi> indeed they are the Channels that
bring water to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> and his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines Mill; the
ſtalking walking Horſes that<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3205:38"/>bring home all the
Provander and proviſion to his <hi>Holines</hi> Kitchen: the Poſts or
Pillers that vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the whole fabrick of their <hi>Maſſes, Miracles,
Proceſsions, Pilgrimages, Dirges,</hi> and the like.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the eight, through the great pittie that he
had vpon the ſilly ſoules burnt and broi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in <hi>Purgatory</hi> (like
dryed Herring, or <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalian</hi> Hammes or Gamons of Bacon which hang
ſeaven yeares long in the ſmoake) by the good and ripe adviſe and
councell of <hi>Odilion</hi> a holy Father and Monke of an Abby called
<hi>Clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> did command and ordaine that alwayes the next day after
<hi>All-hallowes</hi> day,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>All-ſoules</hi> day.</note>
a ſolemne day of devotion ſhould be kept for all Chriſten ſoules: which
order is very preciſely followed and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by our deere mother the holy
Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and many yeares of Pardon given or gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to all
thoſe, which vpon that day doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly viſit the Chantry Prieſts and
Maſſes of <hi>Scali Coeli,</hi> vſing their purſe liberally for that
pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and to haue a trentall of Maſſes, a ſacke full of ſeven
Pſalmes, and three or foure pokes packt with <hi>Pater noſters</hi> and
<hi>Aue Maries,</hi> all well meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and filled, whereof to make a
preſent to the ſilly ſoules in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> for that is fit meate
for their mouths, and they are as well refreſhed with thoſe dainties, as
though they were wrapped a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the head with a wet clout in a cold mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
But yet I will not omit a pretty take for my purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Wee read (quoth the Author of the booke cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Sermones
diſcipuli de tempore</hi>)<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm.</hi> 41.</note> that
in old time<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3205:38"/>good people would on <hi>All-hallowen</hi> day
take bread and deale for all Chriſten ſoules. And one good Woman a widdow,
who had in ſtore but three pecks of flower, did make it all into loaues and
deale it, ſaying to them that receiued it, Remember to pray for the ſoule
of my Mother. And one of them praying very earneſtly for the ſoule of this
good Womans Mother, her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appeared vnto her and told her, my daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by
her charitie and thou by thy good prayers haſt now helped me out of
<hi>Purgatory;</hi> Tell my daughter that ſhee ſell her Cow and goe
preſently to <hi>Rome</hi> to the <hi>Popes Holines</hi> for a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for
her ſinnes, and then ſhee may be eaſed of ſuch paines as I haue
indured: which being told to her daughter, ſhee reioyced much and did as
ſhee was bidden, and went to <hi>Rome,</hi> and had <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</hi> And
the <hi>Pope</hi> by divine revelation knew before ſhee came of all that had
happened to her.<note place="margin">This Tale is alledged by Father
<hi>Steuens</hi> in his Booke called <hi>The V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Gods Church.</hi> pag.
271.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Let me then intreat all honeſt <hi>Engliſh Italiana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
Romaniſts,</hi> who are willing to chaffer for this ſingular, exquiſite
commoditie of <hi>Indulgence</hi> at the beſt hand in this next enſuing
yeare of <hi>Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lee,</hi> that they provide them of good ſtore of caſh;
though I heare <hi>Pardons</hi> will be then very plenty, and therefore the
leſſe dainty.</p>
               <p>The <hi>prices</hi> they ſhall find high or low accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to
the courſeneſſe or fineneſſe of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, the
lightneſſe or weightineſſe of the crime, the abilitie or weakneſſe
of the purchaſer. I haue within theſe few daies ſeene in the hands
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3205:39"/>of one (who eſteemeth it as a great raritie) an
au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticall Booke of the particular Prices and Taxations of all Pardons,
Faculties, and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences grantable by the <hi>Popes</hi> liberall
<hi>Holines,</hi> which Booke was Printed aboue an hundred yeares agoe in
<hi>Paris,</hi> bearing the name of <hi>Taxa Came<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e Apoſtolicae,</hi> which as I gueſſe is like to
be publiſhed in <hi>Engliſh</hi> ere long againſt the opening of the
great Market, for the benefit of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world. And ſure a great
benefit it is and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall conveniency to our <hi>Romaniſts</hi> who are
wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to trade, to know before hand the prices of the Market by the Booke of
the generall Bailiffe, or Clearke of the Market. It is defended by ſome
Writers<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deſeuſio Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſien. Curi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> pro libertate Eccl. Gall.
Ludouic.</hi> 11. <hi>Oblato a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus.</hi> 77.</note> that the common
<hi>Indulgences</hi> onely, with the Letters of pardon, and the
<hi>Reſeruationes pectorales, mentales, regreſſus generales &amp;
ſpeciales acceſſus,</hi> with other ſuch trifles more, are worth to the
<hi>Pope</hi> in one onely Kingdome aboue two hundred thouſand Crownes a
yeare: which through all Chriſtendome would amount to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue tenne millions
of Crownes, which is a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie moderate reckoning or ſumme. I haue beene
informed by ſome of the <hi>Prieſts</hi> in <hi>London</hi> that ſome
great perſons of our Kingdome haue ſent the Pope two or three hundred
pounds a piece for Pardons. The vſe of ſome of which Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences in the
manner of their proceedings is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry remarkable. For they are the Mother or
Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife of many wicked practiſes, for the advantage of their Church, as
being the very bellowes which blow the fire of Treaſon againſt the
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3205:39"/>and ſtates of Princes. This ware bewitcheth not
onely private men, but great <hi>Kings;</hi> For <hi>her Merchants are the
great men of the earth.</hi> Apoc. 18. 3. Therefore infinite ſtore of this
<hi>Babylonian</hi> trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery was tranſported vnto the poore
<hi>Indians,</hi> for the pretended benefit of their ſoules, but for the
intended benefit of a Princes worldly eſtate.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Miniſtration</hi> of the Popes pardons is with the
ingredients of <hi>Parchment, Waxe,</hi> and <hi>encaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Words,</hi> all
which by purging the entrailes of their purſes haue a wonderfull operation in
them.</p>
               <p>The Treaſury of <hi>Indulgences</hi> is ſhut vp in a Cheſt
(his <hi>Holines</hi> having the Keyes) wherein is heaped vp all the
ſuperfluous meritorious good workes of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Francis,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
                  <hi>Benedict,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <hi>Dominick,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
                  <hi>Thomas a
Becket,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Boniface,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Alphonſe,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy
Fathers,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Petrus Aſores in Catholica
aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertione de lege.</hi>
                  </note> whoſe merits being ſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing
plentifull, over and beſide what hath an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered for their owne ſinnes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. Extrauag. Clement.</hi> 6.</note> the
<hi>Pope</hi> diſpenſeth and diſtributeth the remainder to every perſon
according to his <hi>Holines</hi> diſcretion, which is much guided by weight
and meaſure of that which is brought to purchaſe a good Market.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theſaurum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae vocant Chriſti
&amp; ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum, Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> merita. Caluin. Inſtit.
lib.</hi> 3 <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> The bottome of this Cheſt is ſo
vnplummetable, that it can never be ſounded, emptied nor dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. If it
were poſſible that all the people of the world did goe to <hi>Rome</hi> in
one yeare of <hi>Iubilee</hi> that every one might receiue full Indulgence and
Pardon, yet ſhould the ſame Cheſt be no more emptied thereby, then the
Ocean Sea ſhould be with taking out of it one ſpoonfull of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3205:40"/>water; or S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Goddards</hi> mountaines be diminiſhed
by taking from them one handfull of ſand.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tho. Becon. de Reliqu. Eccl. Rom.
ſol.</hi> 186.</note>Laſtly, as for the <hi>extent</hi> of theſe
<hi>Indulgences.</hi> Some of them are for an hundred thouſand yeares, ſo
liberall is the holy Father. Pope <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the 8. granted ſome for
fifty thouſand yeares as but an ordinary kindneſſe; Pope <hi>Clement</hi>
the 7. for fortie thouſand; Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 5. for thirti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thouſand yeares.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plenariae In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgentiae a Papâ
Centoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> annorum: a Cardinalibus centum dieru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ab Epiſcopis
quadraginta.</hi>
                  </note> Some are granted to the <hi>liuing,</hi> ſome to the
<hi>dead.</hi> Some purchaſe pardons as they doe Lands, not onely for
themſelues, but their <hi>heires.</hi> Some haue their <hi>whole</hi>
ſinnes remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſome but <hi>part.</hi> Some haue power granted for the
freeing of <hi>one</hi> ſoule out of <hi>Purgatory</hi> by the <hi>Popes</hi>
Indulgence, others haue libertie to free <hi>many.</hi> Some of their
<hi>diſpenſations</hi> are the <hi>diſsipati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of divine and
humane right; ſome are the diſvniting of naturall and morall bands. Some
are to tye Princes in vnlawfull marriage; ſome to vntie many Subiects from
lawfull obedience: All of them are of great preſumption againſt the Lawes
of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caluin. Inſtitut. lib.</hi> 3.
<hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note>
                  <hi>Sunt ſanguinis Christi prophanatio, Satanae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
ludibrium, quo Chriſtianum populum a Dei gratia, â vita quae est in
Chriſto abdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, &amp; a vera ſalutis via avertant.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:3205:40"/>
               <head>SPECIALL INDVLGENCES PVRCHASED AT <hi>Rome,</hi> granted to
diverſe Engliſh Gentle beleeving <hi>Roman Catholickes,</hi> for their
money.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y chiefe intent in propounding a recitall of particular
<hi>Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> given to diverſe particular men of our Nation, is not
(God is my witnes) to caſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of folly vpon Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of worthy and
reſpected Families in our Nation; but to imply and ſignifie in regard of
the publicke by this taſt and eſſay, what great ſummes of money are
exhauſted and gotten out of this Kingdome to inrich <hi>Rome</hi> vpon
pretence of theſe and other ſuch like Trumperies. They <hi>make a Mart of
the Nations. Eſa.</hi> 23. 3. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall pardons indeed which like
Summer-ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes ſo buſily fly abroad, what are they els then
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3205:41"/>very Nets for money, Impoſtures, Sophiſticati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
Circunductions, Colluſions, and Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings of the people, defacings of
Chriſts death, obſcurings of Gods free grace, very ſpurres vnto all
lewdneſſe of life? For what offence, knavery, ſinne, or abhomination can
be ſo great, which may not be healed and made cleane with the mollifying oyle
of the <hi>Popes</hi> candid <hi>Indulgence?</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>—Venalia Romae</l>
                  <l>Thura, Sacerdotes, caelum eſt venale, Deuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:3205:41"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Jndulgences</hi> granted to <hi>Reliques, Croſſes,
Beades</hi> and <hi>Pictures,</hi> at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Robert
Sherley,</hi> Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour from the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> to all
Chriſtian Princes.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>1</label>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hoſe who having any of
the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid things, ſhall confeſſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, or ſay
Maſſe, and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over ſhall ſay the Pſalme <hi>De profun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi>
with one <hi>Pater Noſter</hi> and one <hi>Aue;</hi> and thoſe that cannot
read, three <hi>Pater noſters</hi> and three <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue's,</hi> gaine a plenary
and deliuer a ſoule out of <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>2</label> Thoſe who ſhall ſay
<hi>The Divine Office,</hi> or <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um B. Mariae,</hi> or 7
<hi>Pſalmes,</hi> or <hi>Coron. of our Lady,</hi> or a third part of the
<hi>Roſary,</hi> or the <hi>Letanies of Saints</hi> with the Prayers, or that
of our <hi>Lady</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, praying our Saviour for the exaltation of holy
Church, and extirpation of hereſie, gaine all the <hi>Indulgences</hi> which
in that day are got in all the Churches within and without the walles of
<hi>Rome,</hi> and a Plenary for thoſe that ſhall be confeſſed and
communicated.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>3</label> Thoſe who ſhall ſay
three <hi>Pater noſters</hi> and three <hi>Aue maries,</hi> praying our
Saviour for the <pb n="78" facs="tcp:3205:42"/>Advancement and Honor of S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Robert
Sherley,</hi> a grand Promotor of the <hi>Catholicke</hi> cauſe, deſiring
alſo the increaſe of all Religious Orders, they are made partakers of all
the Interceſſions of the aforeſaid renowned Knight; as alſo of all the
ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, prayers, faſtings, mortifications, and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous workes of any of
the members of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>4</label> Every time that any one
ſhall examine his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and after the ſame ſhall ſay one
<hi>Pater no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> and one <hi>Aue Marie;</hi> praying for the
exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of holy Church, and extirpation of hereſie, he doth gaine the
Remiſſion of the third part of his ſinnes, and being confeſſed and
communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, ſaying ſeaven <hi>Pater noſters</hi> and ſeaven
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue Maries,</hi> deliver three ſoules out of <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:3205:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Jndulgences</hi> granted to <hi>Croſſes, Beads,</hi>
and <hi>Pictures,</hi> at the inſtance of the Procurators of the
Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Carolo Boromeo.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>1</label>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>IS <hi>Holines</hi> doth
grant to any that ſhall haue about him any of thoſe forenamed things
bleſſed, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before any of the ſaid Pictures, ſhall ſay
<hi>the office of our Ladie,</hi> of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> or of the
<hi>dead,</hi> or the ſeaven Penitentiall <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> or
<hi>graduall,</hi> or the <hi>Coronarie of our Ladie,</hi> or of our
<hi>Sauiour,</hi> or the third part of the <hi>Roſarie,</hi> or ſhall
<hi>heare Maſſe,</hi> or a <hi>Preaching,</hi> or ſhall <hi>viſite</hi>
the moſt holy <hi>Sacrament,</hi> or ſhall accompany it, or ſhall giue an
Almes, or doe any other like workes (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they ſhould be bound to doe
the ſame) praying for the extirpation of hereſie, gaine for every time the
remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the third part of their ſinnes, and being confeſſed, and
communicated, a <hi>plenarie Indulgence, a poena et culpa,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>2</label> His <hi>Holines</hi> doth
alſo grant to every one that ſhall make reverence to any
<hi>Croſſe</hi> or <hi>Picture,</hi> or ſhall recommend himſelfe to
<hi>God,</hi> to our <hi>Ladie,</hi> to his <hi>good Angell,</hi> or to that
<hi>Saint</hi> which he is moſt devoted to, or ſhall giue <hi>thankes</hi>
to God for his benefits received, or in the beginning any action, or in time of
any tribulation ſhall <hi>ſigne</hi>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:3205:43"/>
                  <hi>himſelfe
three times with the ſigne of the holy Croſſe,</hi> or ſhal ſay once
<hi>Deus in adiutorium meum intende,</hi> or ſhall doe other pious or
charitable workes, gaine for every time <hi>twentie yeares of
Indulgence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>3</label> For every one that are
<hi>penitent</hi> for their ſinnes, with purpoſe to Confeſſe them, and
communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, ſhall gaine ten yeares of <hi>Indulgence,</hi> &amp; when
moreover they ſhall examine their conſciences, they gaine
<hi>remiſsion</hi> of the <hi>third part of their ſins,</hi> and being
effectually confeſſed, praying to God for the happie eſtate of holy
Church, gaine <hi>dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>4</label> And every time that any
<hi>Prieſt</hi> ſhall <hi>confeſſe &amp; communicate</hi> or ſay
<hi>Maſſe</hi> (as well being bound as for devotion) and pray to God for
the <hi>extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hereſie,</hi> or the <hi>exaltation of holy
Church,</hi> he ſhall gaine a <hi>plenarie,</hi> and praying for the
<hi>ſoules in Purgatory,</hi> deliver every time a ſoule thence, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to their owne intention.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall cauſe to be ſayd <hi>three
Maſſes</hi> of the dead in one or more dayes twelue times in the yeare; for
every time <hi>deliuereth a ſoule out of Purgatory,</hi> according to his
owne intention.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>5</label> Whoſoever vpon <hi>holy
Thurſday,</hi> and vpon the day of the <hi>Aſcenſion of our Sauiour</hi>
ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and communicate, and ſhall pray for his
<hi>Holines,</hi> and for the exaltation of holy Church, gaineth the
<hi>Indulgences</hi> of the bleſſing of his <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines,</hi> which he is
vſed to giue publickly in that day as if he were preſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>6</label> In the dayes of the
<hi>Stations</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> in what time of the yeare ſoever, who
ſo hath any of the<pb n="81" facs="tcp:3205:43"/>aforeſaid holy things, may gaine the
ſame <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> as well for the <hi>liuing</hi> as the
<hi>dead,</hi> ſaying in the Church, or at home before ſome of the ſayd
Pictures fiue <hi>Pater noſters,</hi> and fiue <hi>Aue's</hi> in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of
the moſt holy blood of our Saviour, ſprinckled in his moſt holy
Paſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>7</label> Whoſoever ſhall ſay
one <hi>Miſerere,</hi> or one <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> &amp;c. or <hi>Te Deum,</hi>
&amp;c. in honor of the <hi>moſt holy blood</hi> as aboue, and <hi>kiſſe
the ground three times,</hi> may be partaker of the <hi>Indulgence</hi> which
they doe gaine, which make the going of the <hi>holy ſtayres</hi> that
day.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>8</label> Thoſe which are preſent
at the moſt holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> and ſhall <hi>pray
for his Holines,</hi> for the <hi>Chriſtian Princes,</hi> and
<hi>tranquilitie of their ſtate,</hi> doe gaine every time all the
<hi>Indulgences</hi> and <hi>Graces</hi> which in that day are got by
viſiting all the Churches within and without <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>9</label> Whoſoever ſhall pray for
the <hi>conſeruation and increaſe of religious Orders,</hi> is made
partaker of all their ſacrifices, faſtings, diſciplines, prayers, and
other their good workes, as if he were a member of any of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>10</label> Whoſoever having
confeſſed and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in the feaſt of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Charles,</hi> ſhall
ſay fiue <hi>Pater noſters</hi> and fiue <hi>Aue's</hi> in honor of the
Paſſion of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> getteth a <hi>plenarie,</hi> and the
remiſſion of all their ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>11</label> Likewiſe his
<hi>Holines</hi> doth grant to thoſe that ſay one <hi>Pater noſter</hi>
and <hi>Aue,</hi> or the <hi>Pſalme Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date Dominum omnes gentes,</hi> or
the Pſalme <hi>De pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundis,</hi> or ſhall kiſſe any of the aboue
named ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <pb n="82" facs="tcp:3205:44"/>things, ſaying three times <hi>Ieſus</hi>
and one <hi>Salve,</hi> Pardon for all thoſe deſerts which they haue
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſedly committed in ſaying the <hi>divine office</hi> (either being
bound thereto or for devotion) or any errour in ſaying <hi>the office of our
Ladie,</hi> or our <hi>Saviour,</hi> or by ſaying or hearing
<hi>Maſſe,</hi> or ſaying or doing any other kinde of ſpirituall
worke.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>12</label> Whoſoever ſhall be
<hi>hindred</hi> by any lawfull cauſe ſo that he cannot be preſent at
<hi>Maſſe,</hi> or that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Prieſt cannot ſay <hi>Maſſe,</hi>
or cannot ſay his <hi>office,</hi> or other things to which he was bound; By
ſaying fiue <hi>Pater noſters</hi> and fiue <hi>Aue's</hi> in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the
moſt ſacred blood of our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſprinkled in his moſt holy
Paſſion, obtaineth the ſame <hi>Indulgence</hi> which he ſhould haue
had in fulfilling the aforeſayd things. Thoſe which at the point of death
devoutly ſay once <hi>Ieſu</hi> with heart, not being able to pronounce it
with their mouths, being therewith contrite, not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be
confeſſed and communicated, obtaine all <hi>Indulgences</hi> in forme of a
<hi>Iubilee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>13</label> Laſtly, his
<hi>Holines</hi> doth grant over and beſide the aboue-named
<hi>Indulgences</hi> and <hi>graces</hi> (of what ſort ſoever they be) that
it ſhall be ſufficient for any one to haue of the aforeſayd holy things
ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>proper</hi> or <hi>borrowed,</hi> and if that it happen any do
breake or be loſt, one other may be put in the place of the ſame, and
ſhall haue the ſame <hi>graces</hi> and <hi>Indulgences,</hi> and that they
doe ſerue for all places of the world, neither are they to be recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
except there be expreſſe mention made of the aforeſaid Chapters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:3205:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Jndulgences</hi> granted to a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of this
Kingdome by the Interceſſion of her Sonne. <hi>Anno Domini</hi>
1607.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>1</label>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>IS <hi>Holines</hi> is
pleaſed to grant that for thirtie yeares following, vpon the ſixt of
<hi>February,</hi> every yeare, in the Church of <hi>Santa Maria Maggiore,</hi>
(which is ſeated vpon one of the ſeaven <hi>Hills,</hi> called <hi>Mons
Eſquilinus</hi>) there ſhall be ſaid that day at the high <hi>Altar</hi>
a <hi>Maſſe</hi> for the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe, and thereby ſhall ſhee
obtaine a <hi>plenary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion</hi> for all her ſinnes paſt. And by
repeating fiue <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> fiue <hi>Aue's,</hi> and one
<hi>Credo,</hi> &amp;c. Shee ſhall be able her ſelfe to free a ſoule that
day out of <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It is granted vnto the ſaid honourable Lady,
that within a private Chappell of the aforeſayd Church, called the
<hi>Splendid Chappell of Pope Paolo</hi> the V. (where he lyeth buried) there
ſhall be ſaid vpon the ſeventh of <hi>February</hi> during the ſpace of
thirtie yeares following, <hi>Maſſes</hi> for the children and kinred of
the ſaid Counteſſe; and by vertue thereof the third part of their
ſinnes ſhall be remitted; And if they be Confeſſed and Communicate the
ſame day, they ſhall obtaine a <hi>plenary Indulgence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:3205:45"/>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>3</label> It
ſhall be lawfull for the ſaid Lady and her Children in time of Lent, and
other times of the yeare in the which white meats be prohibite and forbidden,
to eate egges, cheeſe, milke, butter, and other ſuch like, freely and
without ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſitie; and if they be ſicke they may alſo eate
fleſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>
                  </label> Laſtly, to the aforeſaid Lady
for diverſe her pious workes, eſpecially for her ſuſtentation and
maintenance of a <hi>Holy man</hi> to ſay <hi>Maſſe</hi> daily for the
ſoules in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> ſhee ſhall at the houre of her death haue
full remiſſion of all her ſinnes, exceſſes, and treſpaſſes
whatſoever. <hi>A poena &amp; culpa</hi> &amp;c. The like <hi>Indulgence</hi>
hath ſhee gained for her children, and as many of her kinred as ſhee
ſhall pray for, or wiſh well vnto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:3205:45"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <hi>Jndulgences</hi> granted to the
<hi>Catholickes</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Cardinall
<hi>Allen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>1</label>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>IS <hi>Holines</hi> doth
grant to all the kinred and friends of the ſaid Cardinall (im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing the
<hi>Romiſh Catholick Religion,</hi> and ſaying every day three <hi>Pater
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> and three <hi>Aue Maries</hi>) freedome from the paines of
<hi>Purgatory,</hi> and every one of them who ſhall ſay one <hi>Pater
noſter</hi> and one <hi>Aue</hi> more for the honor of the ſaid <hi>Holy
Cardinall,</hi> ſhall get a <hi>plenary Indulgence</hi> for his friend.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>2</label> Whoſoever ſhall cauſe
to be ſaid three <hi>Maſſes</hi> of the dead in one or more dayes twelue
times in the yeare; For every time delivereth a ſoule out of
<hi>Purgatory,</hi> according to his owne intention.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>3</label> Whoſoever
<hi>Catholicke</hi> of <hi>England</hi> vpon holy <hi>Thurſday</hi> before
<hi>Eaſter,</hi> and <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> of our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> ſhall
be Confeſſed and Communicate, and ſhall pray for his <hi>Holines,</hi>
for the Cardinalls, and for the Exaltation of holy Church, gaineth the
<hi>Indulgences</hi> of the bleſſing of his <hi>Holines,</hi> (which he is
vſed to giue publickly in that day) as if he were preſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>4</label> Whoſoever honoureth our
<hi>Lady</hi> with three <hi>Ave Maria's</hi> in a day more then is inioyned by
his Confeſſor, and once in a weeke ſhall ſay over this Prayer.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:3205:46"/>O domina mea ſancta Maria, mater Dei,
pietate pleniſsima, ſummi Regis filia, mater glorioſiſsima, mater
orphanorum, conſolatio deſolatorum, via erran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, ſalus omnium in te
ſperantium, virgo ante par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, virgo in partu, &amp; virgo poſt partum;
fons miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordiae, fons ſalutis &amp; gratiae, fons conſolationis &amp;
indulgentiae, fons pietatis &amp; laetitiae, fons vitae &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae; hodie
&amp; quotidie, &amp; in hora exitus mei, &amp; ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam meam &amp; corpus meum
tibi commendo: omnem ſpem meam &amp; conſolationem meam, omnes anguſtias
&amp; miſerias meas, vitam &amp; finem vitae meae tibicom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitto. Amen.</q>
               <q>
                  <l>Virgo virginum praeclara</l>
                  <l>Mihi iam non ſis amara.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Whoſoever performeth the premiſſes ſhall receiue many
bleſſings from our <hi>Lady</hi> in this life, and at his death our
<hi>Lady</hi> ſhall appeare vnto him and comfort him.</p>
               <p>His <hi>Holines</hi> doth command all thoſe that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor our
<hi>Lady</hi> to carry about with them, the booke called <hi>Officium B. Mariae
Virginis,</hi> or our <hi>Ladyes Pſalter;</hi> and to keepe our <hi>Ladyes
Beads</hi> and <hi>Pictures.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:3205:46"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Jndulgences</hi> and <hi>Pardons</hi> granted to Sir
<hi>Iohn Markam,</hi> Knight. <hi>Anno Domini.</hi> 1608.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>1</label>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>IS <hi>Holines</hi> doth
grant vnto the ſaid Knight for diverſe his pious and laudable
<hi>acts,</hi> plenary Pardon and Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution for all his ſinnes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
committed; as alſo Impoſſibility for the paines of <hi>Purgatory,</hi>
promiſing him a good Angell al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to attend him: He doth further yeeld
that whoſoever ſhall ſay for the ſoule of S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Iohn Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kam</hi>
(being dead) thrice <hi>Pater Noſter &amp; Aue,</hi> ſhall gaine fortie
dayes of <hi>Indulgence</hi> whatſoever ſinne he commit.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>2</label> His <hi>Holines</hi> doth
further grant to <hi>Katherine</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> ſiſters of the
ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Iohn Markam</hi> comming to Confeſſion and Communicating,
and having any of the Meddalls of this Pardon, ſaying three <hi>Pater
noſters</hi> and three <hi>Aue's,</hi> a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>Indulgence</hi> for the
time paſt; And if to the former they adde a <hi>De profundis,</hi> they
obtaine<pb n="88" facs="tcp:3205:47"/>Pardon for fiftie dayes after, and may deliver a
ſoule out of <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>3</label> The ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Iohn
Markam,</hi> and his Siſters, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Devotion at the houre of their
death (the word) <hi>Ieſus;</hi> or if either of them cannot for the
extreamitie of their traunce pronounce it with the mouth, yet if eyther of the
parties but thinke of that bleſſed name, they obtaine a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<hi>Indulgence</hi> in forme of a <hi>Iubilee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:3205:47"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A <hi>Pardon</hi> granted vnto Maſter
<hi>Rawſon</hi> of <hi>England. Anno Domini</hi> 1608.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſaid M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Rawſon</hi> having devoted himſelfe vnto
the ſervice of the bleſſed Father and Law-maker S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Benedict,</hi>
hath obtained by the Interceſſion of the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Benedict,</hi> (who
did call himſelfe from all worldly tumults to ſerue God alone) a plenary
Pardon for himſelfe, and ſuch <hi>Indulgence</hi> as followeth for all his
brethren the <hi>Catholickes</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>1</label> Whoſoever ſhall ſay
<hi>Sancte Benedicte or a pro me,</hi> with <hi>Pater noſter &amp; Aue,</hi>
ſhall forthwith haue a third part of his ſinnes remitted him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>2</label> Whoſoever ſhall ſay
three <hi>Pater noſters</hi> and three <hi>Aue Maries</hi> for the
advancement and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py increaſe of all the Religious Profeſſors of the
Order of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Benedict,</hi> ſhall participate a particular benefit by all
their ſacrifices, prayers, faſtings, mortification and good workes, as if
he were a particular member of that Religious Order.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>3</label> Whoſoever ſhall
celebrate either by Devotion <pb n="90" facs="tcp:3205:48"/>or Obligation for any part of
that Order, ſhall forthwith deliver a ſoule out of <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>4</label> Whoſoever ſhall
ſacrifice vnto the Diſciples of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Benedict,</hi> that is, to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <hi>Placidus,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Maurus,</hi> the Virgin S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Scholaſtica</hi>
his Siſter, and to all holy <hi>Monkes</hi> and <hi>Nunnes,</hi> ſhall be
able to make warre againſt the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> and the
<hi>Devill,</hi> and inſtantly deliver two ſoules out of
<hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:3205:48"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <hi>Jndulgences</hi> granted by his <hi>Holines</hi>
to the Family of the MANPHILDS in <hi>England. Anno Dominini</hi>
1608.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>1</label>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the dayes of the
Stations of <hi>Rome,</hi> in what time of the yeare ſoever, any of the
aforeſaid Family ſhall pray before any of the ſacred <hi>Reliques</hi>
and <hi>Pictures</hi> ſent from his <hi>Holines,</hi> they ſhall gaine the
ſame <hi>Indulgence</hi> as well for the liuing as the dead, as is giuen that
day publickely at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaying in the Church or at home before
ſome of the ſaid Pictures or Reliques fiue <hi>Pater noſters</hi> and
fiue <hi>Aue Maries,</hi> in honor of the moſt holy blood of our
<hi>Saviour</hi> ſprinckled in his moſt holy Paſſion.<note place="margin">Of little worth is that skull or dead mans bone which vvill not
(by beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming a holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique) adde ſomething to the Popes
Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>2</label> For ſaying one
<hi>Miſerere,</hi> or one <hi>Credo,</hi> or <hi>Te Deum,</hi> &amp;c. in
honor of the moſt holy blood as aboue, and kiſſing the ground three
times, any of the aforeſaid Family may be partaker of the
<hi>Indulgences</hi> which they doe gaine who make the going of the <hi>holy
Stayres</hi> that day.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">indulgence </seg>3</label> Whoſoever of the
aforeſaid Family having Confeſſed and Communicated, ſhall ſay this
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:3205:49"/>
                  <hi>Antiphon</hi> in honor of our <hi>Lady,</hi> gaineth a
<hi>plenary,</hi> and ſhall free a ſoule out of <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                     <body>
                        <div type="antiphon">
                           <lg>
                              <l>Aue Regina coelorum,</l>
                              <l>Aue Domina Angelorum:</l>
                              <l>Salue radix, ſalue porta,</l>
                              <l>Ex qua mundo lux est orta.</l>
                              <l>Gaude virgo glorioſa,</l>
                              <l>Super omnes ſpecioſa;</l>
                              <l>Vale ô valde decora,</l>
                              <l>Et pro nobis Chriſtum exora.</l>
                           </lg>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:3205:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Indulgences</hi> granted to the Family of the Lord
<hi>M.</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> at the Interceſſion of <hi>Tob.
Mathew. Anno Domini.</hi> 1608.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>IS <hi>Holines</hi> hath granted vnto the ſaid Lord
<hi>M.</hi> for the reliefe he hath af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorded vnto diſtreſſed
<hi>Catholickes,</hi> as alſo for his bountie to the houſes of
<hi>Bruxells</hi> and <hi>Liſbon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">I wiſh rather that
this Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh money had bin ſpent in <hi>England</hi> vpon ſome publicke
ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice there.</note> and for yeelding his hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping hand to the repaire of
the Churches of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Peters, Santa Maria Maggiore,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Pauls,</hi>
S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtian</hi> and <hi>Fabian,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Lawrance, Santa
Croce,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Iohn de Lateran</hi> neare <hi>Rome,</hi> that he ſhall
be partaker of all the <hi>Maſſes, Prayers, Faſtings, Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings,
Pilgrimages,</hi> &amp;c. had at the Stations of <hi>Rome;</hi> together with a
<hi>plenary Remiſsion</hi> of all ſinnes, <hi>A poena &amp; culpa,</hi>
&amp;c. for a thouſand Lents and ſixtie-fiue yeares. And beſides
ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any day of the yeare three <hi>Pater Noſters</hi> and three
<hi>Aue's</hi> more then is commanded him by his ghoſtly Father, he ſhall
be able to free one of his Friends out of <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:3205:50"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Indulgences</hi> very large granted to the Family of the
Lord <hi>W.</hi> at the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the ſaid <hi>T. M.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
                  <hi>Indulgences</hi> granted to the Family of the Lord
<hi>Va.</hi> at the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of <hi>T. M.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:3205:50"/>
               <head>A PARDON GRAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TED TO <hi>THO: GER.</hi> OF England Knight,
and his Lady.</head>
               <div type="original">
                  <p>PAulus quintus Epiſcopus, ſervus ſervorum Dei: Dilecto
filio nobili viro <hi>Tho. Ger.</hi> Militi; &amp; dilectae in Chriſto filiae
nobili mulieri ejus uxori, ſalutem &amp; Apoſtolicam bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictionem,
&amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="translation">
                  <head> The ſame at large in Engliſh thus:</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PAul</hi> the fift, Biſhop, ſeruant of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants
of God: To his beloued ſonne the noble Gentleman <hi>T. G.</hi> the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
Knight; and to his beloued daughter in Chriſt the noble Lady his wife,
greeting and Apoſtolicall benediction. Hauing heard of late of ſome
deſires of yours which concerne the ſaluation of your<pb n="96" facs="tcp:3205:51"/>ſoules, and receiuing your Petitions from the hands of the Religious
man <hi>Henry Stanley,</hi> we haue granted to your ſaid Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions a
fauourable hearing, and by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of theſe preſents doe grant this
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence to your deuotion. That ſuch a ghoſtly Father as either of you
ſhal chuſe, ſhall haue power by Apoſtolicall authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to grant to
you full remiſſion of all your ſinnes whereof you ſhall be
confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as alſo freedome from the paines of Purgatory. And euery
Wedneſday, Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, or Saturday that any of you ſhall ſay ouer the
<hi>Office of our Lady,</hi> you ſhall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit for whom you loue beſt. And
if vpon Eaſter day you ſhal be confeſſed and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate,</hi> and
ſay <hi>nine Pater-noſters,</hi> and <hi>nine Aues,</hi> with a <hi>de
profundis,</hi> for the ſoules in Purgatory, you ſhall euerie time be able
to free one ſoule thence. Alſo at the houre of your death the Deuill
ſhall haue no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer you, nor at al trouble or torment you. What lawfull
petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhall ask at any time of God, he ſhal grant it you. Your
enemies ſhall not preuaile againſt you. Yet<pb n="97" facs="tcp:3205:51"/>we declare
that if vpon confidence of this Remiſſion, you ſhall commit any
notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſinnes wilfully, that then this preſent Pardon ſhall not helpe
you as concerning them. You muſt alſo perſiſt in the vnitie and faith
of the holy Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and pray for the extirpation of hereſie,
and liue in obedience and deuotion towards vs &amp; our ſucceſſors Popes
of <hi>Rome,</hi> cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nically entring into that Sea, and further doe your
dutie to all religious men. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you ſhall giue twentie ſhillings
yearlie towards the maintenance of the Cope of S. <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> and
euery Friday a penie to the firſt poore bodie you meet. Let it now be lawful
for no man to infringe this Pardon and Grant of ours, or with any boldneſſe
to contradict it. And if anie ſhal preſume to attempt any ſuch thing, let
him know and aſſured lie vnderſtand, that hee ſhall incurre the
indignation of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, and of his bleſſed Apoſtles Saint
<hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> &amp; all other Martyrs and Saints.
Giuen at S. Peters in Rome, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Fiſhers Ring, the 9 of Aprill, in the
firſt yeare of our Papacy.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:3205:52"/>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The forme of the Abſolution wherewith they are abſolued
with whom his Holineſſe ſo graciouſly diſpenſeth.</head>
                  <div type="original">
                     <p>AVthoritate Dei Patris Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potentis, &amp; beatorum
<hi>Petri &amp; Pauli</hi> Apoſtolorum ejus, ac autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate Apoſtolica
mihi in hac parte commiſſa: Ego abſolvote abomnibus peccatis tuis mihi
per te vere confeſsis &amp; contritis, &amp; de quibus confiteri v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lles; ſi tuae occurrerent memoriae.
Plenariam abſolutionem omnium peccatorum tuorum, in quantum cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves
Eccleſiae ſe extendunt in hac par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, authoritate iſtarum literarum
A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicarum tibi do &amp; concedo, ita ut ſis abſolutus ante Tribunal
Domini noſtri Jeſu Chriſti, habeaſque vitam aeternam, &amp; vivas in
ſecula ſeculoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="translation">
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:3205:52"/>
                     <head>In Engliſh thus:</head>
                     <p>BY the authoritie of God the Father Almightie, &amp; of his
bleſſed Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and by the
Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique authoritie committed vnto mee in this behalfe: I abſolue thee
from all thy ſinnes, by thee to mee trulie confeſſed and contrite, and of
which thou wouldſt haue been confeſſed, if they had come vnto thy
remembrance. Moreouer I giue and grant vnto thee full abſolution and
remiſſion of all thy ſinnes, ſo farre as the keies of the Church doe
extend in this behalfe by the authoritie of theſe Apoſtolique Letters, ſo
that thou be abſolued before the iudging ſeat of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,
and haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life, worlds without end. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:3205:53"/>
                  <head>Another forme of Abſolution.</head>
                  <div type="original">
                     <p>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>thoritate Dei Patris Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potentis, Apoſtolorum Petri
&amp; Pauli, &amp; totius matris Eccleſiae: ac virtute hujus Bullae &amp;
Papalis Jndulgentiae, Ego abſolvo te ab om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus peccatis tuis, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="translation">
                     <p>BY the authoritie of God the Father Almightie, of the
Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and of all the mother Church, and
by vertue of this Bull, the Popes Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, I abſolue thee from all thy
ſinnes, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:3205:53"/>
                  <head>A third forme of Abſolution.</head>
                  <div type="original">
                     <p>AVthoritate Dei Omnipotentis, &amp; beatorum <hi>Petri &amp;
Pauli</hi> Apoſtolorum ejus, ac authoritate Apoſtolica mihi in hac parte
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſa: Ego abſolvo te ab omnibus pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catis tuis &amp; poenistibi in
Purgatorio debitis propter culpas &amp; offenſas quas contra Deum &amp;
animam tuam com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſiſti. Et in quantum mihi com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur, reſtituo te
illi Jnnocentiae, in qua eras quando baptizatus fuiſti, exceptis punctis hiis
reſervatis Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Papae, ut anima tua vivat cum Chriſto in ſecula
ſeculorum. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="translation">
                     <p>BY the authority of God Almighty, and of his bleſſed
Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and by the Apoſto like
authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie committed vnto me in this behalfe, I<pb n="110" facs="tcp:3205:54"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="101" facs="tcp:3205:54"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <pb n="102" facs="tcp:3205:55"/>abſolue thee
from all thy ſins and paines due vnto thee in Purgatorie for the faults and
offences which thou haſt committed againſt God and thine owne ſoule. And
as much as lieth in my power, I reſtore thee vnto that Innocencie wherein
thou wert when thou waſt baptiſed, thoſe points onely excepted, which are
reſerued to the Lord Pope, that thy ſoule may liue with Chriſt worlds
without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:3205:55"/>
               <head>Generall Pardons granted by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Popes for diuers
conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pope Innocent</hi> the 8, hath granted to euery man and
woman that beareth the length vpon him of Chriſts nayles wherewith hee was
faſtned to the Croſſe (the iuſt length of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them was nine
inches) and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth them daily with fiue <hi>Pater noſters,</hi> and
fiue <hi>Aues,</hi> and a <hi>Creed,</hi> that hee ſhall haue granted him
theſe ſeuen great gifts that follow.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, <hi>Hee ſhall neuer die ſudden nor euill
death.</hi> The ſecond is, <hi>He ſhall neuer bee ſlaine with ſword nor
weapon.</hi> The third is, <hi>His enemies ſhall neuer ouercome him.</hi> The
fourth is, <hi>Poiſon nor falſe witneſſe ſhall neuer grieue him.</hi>
The fiſt is, <hi>He ſhall haue ſufficient goods and honeſt liuing.</hi>
The ſixt is, <hi>He ſhall not die without the Sacraments of the
Church.</hi> The ſeuenth is, <hi>He ſhall be delivcred &amp; defended from
all wicked ſpirits, peſtilence, feuers, and other maladies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:3205:56"/>
                  <hi>Pope Jnnocent</hi> the 8,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>TO all good Chriſtian people diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſay our Ladies
Pſalter within this Church or churchyard, on any of theſe beads, the which
haue beene par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned at the holie place of <hi>Shene,</hi> ſhall haue ten
thouſand yeares of pardon. Alſo for euerie word in the <hi>Pater noſter,
Aue,</hi> and <hi>Credo,</hi> 23 daies of pardon, <hi>totiens,
quotiens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo they are pardoned at Sion, and by that ye ſhall haue
for euery <hi>Pater noſter, Aue,</hi> and <hi>Credo</hi> ſaid on them,
three hundred dayes of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. Alſo vnto all thoſe that the beads do
ſtring, or cauſe to be ſtringed in time of neceſſity, there is
granted by two Biſhops foureſcore dayes of pardon, and Gods bleſſing
and theirs.</p>
               <p>Alſo you muſt ſay firſt on the fiue beads fiue <hi>Pater
noſters,</hi> fiue <hi>Aue Maries,</hi> and a <hi>Creed,</hi> in the
worſhip of the 5 wounds of our Sauiour Chriſt, and then after euery
<hi>Creed,</hi> ſay on the firſt white bead of the fiue <hi>Ieſu for thy
holy name,</hi> and then on the red bead <hi>And for thy bitter paſsion,</hi>
then on the firſt black bead <hi>Saue vs from ſin &amp; ſhame:</hi> then
on the ſecond black bead <hi>And endleſſe damnation:</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:3205:56"/>and then on the laſt white <hi>bead Bring vs to the
bliſſe, That neuer ſhall miſſe Sweet Ieſu, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Pardon wherof, remembring the wounds great and ſmall of
our Sauiour Chriſt, is 5 thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, 4 hundred, 75 yeares, of theſe 5
beads. The whole ſumme of pardon granted of both Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries for euery
Pſalter ſaying on theſe beads, is 26 thouſand, 6 hundred yeares, and 50
dayes, <hi>totiens, quotiens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore let no man nor woman preſume to carrie away or to
conuey the aforeſaid beads, but hang them againe where yee find them. For if
they doe, they are accurſed foure times in the yeare in the generall
ſentence. And at euery Pſalters end, pray for all chriſten ſoules.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 7, with diuers other holy Fathers
Popes of Rome his predeceſſors, of their paternall holineſſe and
abundant graces, haue granted to all the brethren &amp; ſiſterne of the
ſaid gyld that now be, and to all other that will bee, full power and
authority to chuſe them any able Prieſt to their Confeſſor, ſecular
or religious, which may heare their confeſſions, and giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them once
in their life and in the Article of death, plenary and full remiſſion of
all their ſins, exceſſes, offences, and treſpaſſes, how grieuous
and enorme ſoeuer they be, <hi>à poena &amp; culpa,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Againe the brethren and ſiſterne of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:3205:57"/>gyld, may ſay or cauſe to be ſaid, Maſſes and
all other diuine Seruices before day light in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent after three of the
clock after midnight not onely in hallowed places, but alſo in vnhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
places, though they bee ſuſpended or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdicted by ordinary
authority.</p>
               <p>Alſo euery brother and ſiſter that will ſay any
Wedneſday, Friday, or Saturday, one <hi>Pater no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> one <hi>Aue
Maria,</hi> and a <hi>Credo,</hi> in any Church or Chappell where they doe
dwell, prouided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way that they giue ſomewhat to the aforeſaid gyld, and
put-to their helping hand to the ſuſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and maintenance of the
charges of the ſaid gyld, as oft as they ſhall ſo doe, ſhall haue
cleane remiſſion <hi>à poena &amp; culpa,</hi> and the ſame
remiſſion as if they had viſited the Chappell of <hi>Scala coeli</hi> of
Rome, and the Church of S. <hi>Iohn Lateranenſe,</hi> when the Stations there
be celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the quicke and dead.<note place="margin">The picture of Saint
<hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> and a ſtone, will driue away an angry
dog.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The aforeſaid brethren and ſiſterne alſo cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
Maſſe to be ſaid either on the Wedneſday, Friday, or Saturday, in
Church or Chappell for the dead, ſhall deliuer what ſoules they will, and
as oft as they will out of Purgatory.</p>
               <p>They may alſo lawfully in time of Lent and other times of the
yeare, in the which white meats be prohibited and forbidden, eat egges,
cheeſe, milke, butter, and all other white meats, freely &amp; without
ſcrupuloſity or grudge of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: and if they be ſicke, they
alſo may eate fleſh with counſell of their Ghoſtly father and
Phyſitian.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:3205:57"/>And whoſoeuer ſhall procure any man or
woman to bee brother or ſiſter of the aforeſaid gyld, ſhall haue for
his godly trauell fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares of pardon. Alſo euery brother and
ſiſter, with their fathers and mothers departed, ſhall be made partakers
of all Maſſes, Mattenſes, Prayers, Suffrages, Almes deeds, holy liuings,
Pilgrimages, and all other good deeds &amp; works of piety and charitie, the
which be done and ſhal be done throughout the whole vniuerſal Church
militant, and all the members of the ſame for euer. And furthermore, our
ſaid holy Father hath granted to all Chriſtian people, being truly
pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent and confeſſed, or hauing purpoſed to bee confeſſed, at
ſuch times as the Law hath determined, and there deuoutly doe viſit the
Chappell of our Lady in Goſton, and alſo doe viſit three times ſeuen
Altars there aſſigned in the Pariſh Church at the Feaſts of the
glorious Aſſumption, Natiuity, and all other feaſts of the ſame our
bleſſed Lady, or within eight dayes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing after euery of the ſame
Feaſts, or any day of the ſaid Vtas, putting-to their helping hands to the
maintenance of the charges of the ſame gyld, ſhall haue and enioy all and
ſingular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences and Remiſſions of their ſinnes, as if they had
perſonally viſited the Church of the holy Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and
<hi>Paul</hi> at Rome, and other the 7 principal Churches the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> in the year of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile and Grace, and
alſo ſhal haue al the ſame In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences and Remiſſions of their
ſinnes as they ſhould haue if they had perſonally viſited the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:3205:58"/>Church of S. <hi>Iames</hi> in <hi>Compoſtell</hi> in
<hi>Spains,</hi> and had done or cauſed to bee done there any other thing for
the obtaining of the Indulgences of the ſaid yeere of Iubile at <hi>Rome</hi>
and <hi>Compoſtell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo our holy Father hath declared and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, that theſe
ſaid Remiſſions, Faculties, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, and Diſpenſations, ſhall
neuer be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked, ſuſpended, nor denulled, but euer to ſtand in full
ſtrength and vertue, from henceforth, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the yeare of Iubile
at <hi>Rome,</hi> or any other manner of cauſe whatſoeuer ſhall happen in
time to come.</p>
               <p>And euery man or woman may bee made a brother and ſiſter of
<hi>Goſton</hi> gyld, and enioy all Remiſſions, Priuiledges, Liberties,
&amp;c. if they will pay euery one of them at their entring ſixe ſhillings
eight pence, and euery yeare after, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his or her life, eight pence, or
elſe thirteene ſhillings foure pence for the whole, for euery ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular
perſon, towards the maintaining &amp; ſuſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Prieſts,
Clerkes, and poore bead-men, which daily be found with the charges of the
ſaid gyld.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 5 granted to ſo many as giue ought
to the ſuſtentation of the order of S. Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Houndſlow,</hi>
his bleſſing for euer, and twelue yeares, a hundred and threeſcore dayes
of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, with relaxations of the third part of their penance, and of the
paines due for their ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:3205:58"/>Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 4, to all the
brethren and ſiſterne of the aforeſaid order, that giueth ſome good
portion of their goods yeerly to the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren or Meſſengers of the ſaid
order, or in their Will and Teſtament do giue and bequeath ſome honeſt
portion of ſubſtance for the reliefe of the ſaid brethren, hath
licenſed &amp; granted, to chooſe vnto them any apt and meet Prieſt to
bee their Confeſſor or ghoſtly Father,<note place="margin">I aduiſe them
to take M. <hi>Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calfe</hi> for the men, M. <hi>Leake</hi> for
Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> &amp; to abſolue them from all their ſinnes,
<hi>toties, quoties,</hi> and alſo to be buried in Chriſtian buriall, of
whatſoeuer death he deceaſed, if he were not excommunicated by name.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third diſpenſeth with the
brethren and ſiſterne of the aforeſaid Order con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all vowes of
abſtinence, and of pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage going, except onely the vow of pilgrimage vnto
<hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> at Rome, and Saint <hi>Iames</hi> at
Compoſtell, ſo that it ſhall be lawfull for them to change thoſe vowes
of abſtinence and pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, vnto other workes of mercy and charity; and
this hath hee done of his ſpeciall grace and meere motion to al them that
giue ſomewhat to the ſaid Order of Saint Trinitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:3205:59"/>Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth hath
granted to all brethren and ſiſterne of the aforeſaid order, and to all
their parents and friends, whether they be, aliue or dead, all thoſe
Indulgences and Pardons
<note place="margin">Pardons innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable, and good
cheape.</note>(which are innumerable, and may iuſtly be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the
Starres of the sky, and the ſands of the Sea) that they haue, which goe on
pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage either vnto Rome, or vnto the holy Land.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the 2 hath granted and giuen to the
aforeſaid brethren and ſiſterne, once in their life plenary remiſsion,
and full forgiueneſſe of all their ſinnes, yea, and that in all ſuch
caſes as are reſerued to the Apoſtolique Sea.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Very graciou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently
conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note>Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the eight hath confirmed all the
aforeſaid priuiledges, indulgences, pardons, &amp;c. and of his ſpeciall
grace hath doubled them all for the ſaluation of the brethren and
ſiſterne of the Order of S. Trinity.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pardon of the Auguſtine Fryers.</note>Pope
<hi>Iohn</hi> the 23 granted to ſo many as bee brothers and ſiſters, and
benefactors of the Friers Hermites of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that they
ſhall bee partakers of all the prayers, ſacrifices, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
contemplations, faſtings, watchings, pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, vowes, obedience,
chaſtity, pouerty, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, mercy, almes, and of all other ſpirituall
la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, trauels, paines, exerciſes, &amp;c. that bee done either of the
Friers of the aforeſaid order, or of any other deuout and religious people
througout the world, with Remiſsion and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe<pb n="111" facs="tcp:3205:59"/>of all their ſinnes, <hi>à poena &amp; culpa, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
quoties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like pardon was granted of diuers Popes to the Fraternity of
Burton Lazare, with diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of vowes, and relaxation of fome part of
penance, with plenary remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The clemency of Pope <hi>Clement</hi> to
ſuch as are bountifull to S. <hi>Mary</hi> of Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuall.</note>To them that
gaue any thing to the Hoſpitall of Saint <hi>Mary</hi> of Runciuall nigh vnto
Charing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croſſe without the wals of London, Pope <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the 4
granted that they ſhould be partakers of all the Maſſes, Prayers,
Faſtings, Watchings, Pilgrimage-goings vnto the holy Land conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate with
the blood of Chriſt, or vnto the City of Rome, priuiledged with the authority
of the bleſſed Martyrs and Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul.</hi> And
if they be Prieſts or Religious perſons, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men or women, and haue
failed to ſay their diuine Seruice, either through negligence or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of
bookes, or ſickneſſe of body; the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid holy Father doth
mercifully abſolue them from al ſuch offences, and releaſe them from the
paine and puniſhment due vnto ſuch offendors.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Money is the Merchant in all the Popes
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires.</note>Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 6, of his ſpeciall grace hath
giuen and granted to all them that giue ſome part of their ſubſtance,
being confeſſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite, releaſe of the third part enioyned them by
their ghoſtly father, and three yeares of pardon, with an hundred daies more
of pardon, with free buriall in places although interdict, and of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
kind of death they chance to die, with 2000 Lents, and 85 dayes of pardon,
&amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:3205:60"/>Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the third hath
granted to all them that giue ought to the maintenance of the Collegiate Church
of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> of Beuerley an hundred dayes of pardon, and relaxation
from the ſeuenth part of their penance.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth hath granted to all the
brethren of the ſame fraternity, pardon of all ſinnes forgotten, and of all
vowes broken, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the vow vnto the Holy land, and at their latter end
remiſſion from all their ſinnes, <hi>à poena &amp; culpa:</hi>
ſo that to euery brother and ſiſter of that fraternity, being
confeſſed and abſolued, their Confeſſor may ſay on this manner:
<q>
                     <l>Iohn or Ioan, as free I make thee,</l>
                     <l>As heart may thinke, or eye may ſee.</l>
                  </q> Of this
pardon it is alſo thus written:
<q>
                     <l>Omnibus in annis qui turbant jura Ioannis:</l>
                     <l>Ter execrantur, damnati jure probantur.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The pardon granted to the Fraternitie of S. <hi>Cornelis</hi> at
Weſtminſter for ſuch as giue any thing vnto it, commeth in the year to
two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, ſeuen hundred and threeſcore dayes for euer to endure.</p>
               <p>To the Fraternity of the Sepulchre of our L. Ieſus Chriſt,
haue been granted by diuers Popes of Rome, eſpecially Pope <hi>Vrban</hi> the
4, as large Indulgences as any of the former: pardons for 20, 30, and 40
thouſand yeares, with odde daies.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:3205:60"/>
            <div type="discourse">
               <head>A DISCOVRSE OF ENGLISH NVNNES of late tranſported within
theſe two or three yeares.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is obſerued, that cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Fowlers</hi> when they haue
caught one bird in their net, will make vſe of that for a ſtale to tole-on
others. And ſo it is with our <hi>Prieſts &amp; Ieſuits</hi> who entice
the daughters of diuers of our Gentry here in <hi>England</hi> to the Nunneries
beyond the Seas: They not onely tranſport them thither, as it were with a
<hi>Writ</hi> called <hi>Corpus cum cauſa, (them with and for their
money)</hi> but alſo make vſe of thoſe that are in the Cage already, that
they may ſeeme to ſing out the praiſes of the place where they are. And
to this end the <hi>Mother Abbeſſe</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:3205:61"/>by the
direction of an inſpecting ſpirituall father maketh them write ouer
letters, or rather indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth letters in their name to the exceeding mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying
of the ſtate wherein they liue, that other young Birds of that brood,
remaining in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</hi> may be drawn to flie to the ſame forain
neſts.</p>
               <p>I haue ſeene of late diuers letters written from diuers
<hi>Nunnified Gentlewomen</hi> to ſome of their kindred here in this
Kingdome: The ſubiect of which Letters, though from diuers hands, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
concerned, firſt the extolling of thoſe places wherein they were ſetled;
ſecondly, the earneſt requiring and demanding of great ſummes of money to
be ſent ouer at appointed times.</p>
               <p>For the former, I enuy them not that mopiſh, mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kiſh,
fooliſh paradice into which their ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fathers haue brought them, but
am content they ſhall ſolace themſelues with the ioy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of
their Angelicall life.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſummes of money which paſſe out of
our Kingdome to the Nunneries.</note>But as concerning the other, I wiſh it
were duly conſidered of, what infinit ſummes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney paſſe out of our
kingdome yearly, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line thoſe ſaid Nunneries. I haue beene credibly
informed, and ſome of the Prieſts (namely, <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Floud</hi> Ieſuit,
their prime <hi>Procurator,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) haue boaſted in my hearing,
that the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall penſions giuen by our popiſh Voluntaries to ſuch
vſes, amount to the full value of foure thouſand pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, beſides the rich
portions which many of our Engliſh women carry ouer with them, and muſt
ſacrifice and lay downe to the <hi>Lady Abbeſſe</hi> her ſhrine, before
they be accepted<pb n="115" facs="tcp:3205:61"/>of or admitted into their religious Cell,
<hi>unde (ut ab Inferno) nulla eſt redemptio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The places to which our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh women are
ſent. </note>The chiefe places of receipt for our Engliſh women, are
<hi>Bruxels, Griueling,</hi> and <hi>Lisbon.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ſeuerall Orders of Nunnes.</note>The
ſeuerall <hi>Couents</hi> of <hi>Nunnes</hi> there are of <hi>S. Clares</hi>
order, <hi>S. Bridgets</hi> or <hi>S. Brides</hi> order, <hi>S. Katherines</hi>
order of <hi>Sene, Iuſtinians</hi> order, <hi>Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens</hi> order, and
<hi>Auguſtines</hi> order.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that haue but a little or no portion, are packt by their
Maſters to <hi>Griueling</hi> to the poore bare-footed <hi>Clares. Mary
Wiltſhire,</hi> the daughter of a poore Taylor, whom I ſpake of in my other
Booke, being but a ſeruant and a poore wench, ſhe ſhould haue beene
ſeated in this lower form, being of the courſer thred.</p>
               <p>Thoſe of a moderate portion trudge away to <hi>Lisbon,</hi>
where the whole Nunnery is allowed daily 5 crownes and their bread, with ſome
other almes vpon occaſion beſtowed vpon them, as when they ſhew the head
of S. <hi>Vrſula,</hi> the bones of S. <hi>Bridget</hi> and her daughter,
ſundry reliques of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the milke of our Lady, the blood
of <hi>Hales,</hi> with diuers ſuch trinkets and conceits.</p>
               <p>But thoſe that haue a good round ſumme for their dowry (as
1000 or 2000 pounds, which ſome good cuſtomers cary hence) ſuch are
ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for Bruxels, where the hungry Ieſuits (who ſometimes meet with
as good booties as the Merchants of Argier) diſpoſſeſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all
world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cares and vanities, and like ſubtile Alchimiſts refine them out of
their ſiluer and golden droſſe into a more ſublime eſtate and
condition.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:3205:62"/>I haue ſeene within theſe few dayes
Letters that came from <hi>M.C. E.C.</hi> and <hi>A I.</hi> Nunnes at
<hi>Bruxels</hi> to ſome of their kindred in <hi>England.</hi> One of them
writes for fiue hundred pounds: That the Abbeſſe had done a great fauour in
taking ſo little: That the Nunnery is poore, and that the Abbeſſe cannot
forbeare the money any longer.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth appointed a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of
inlarged, vncloiſtred, vbiquitary Votiſts of ſeuerall ſodalities: A
great many of which we haue latent in our kingdome; and of whom the Prieſts
and Ieſuits make great vſe. For theſe are the ſcraping Mendicants, who
bring good ſtore of prouender to the <hi>Ignatian</hi> cratch. Their labor is
to beg what they can get for their holy fathers or maſters, and to doe them
all kinds of ſeruice, as to ſtarch their linnen, ſweepe their chambers,
make their beds, waſt their Church ſtuffe, &amp;c of which ranke are
Miſtris <hi>Baily</hi> in Grayes Inne Lane, <hi>Clarentia</hi> the Maid,
Miſtris <hi>Halſal</hi> in Bloomesbury, Miſtris <hi>Venetia,</hi>
Miſtris <hi>Philpot,</hi> Miſtris <hi>Fowler,</hi> Miſtris <hi>Floud</hi>
in Holborne, <hi>Black Beſſe,</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>As for the beginning of <hi>Nunnes.</hi> When <hi>Pope Iohn</hi>
the firſt was made Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> Monke <hi>Bennet, aliàs
Benedict,</hi> after that hee had placed himſelfe and his Monkiſh brethren
in a certaine noble &amp; famous Cloyſter, built vpon the Mount
<hi>Caſsinus,</hi> raiſed vp alſo an Order of Nunnes, and made his
ſiſter <hi>Scholaſtica</hi> Abbeſſe ouer them.</p>
               <p>Their Apparell is commonly a blacke, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:3205:62"/>a gray coat, cloake, coule, and vaile. They may not reade
the holy Scripture without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or permiſſion of their ſuperior.
Their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are all wrapped full of ſuperſtition and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie,
ſeeking their ſaluation, not in Chriſt through <hi>faith,</hi> but in
mens inuentions by foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and popiſh workes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="list_of_women_transported_to_overseas_nunneries">
               <pb facs="tcp:3205:63"/>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:3205:63"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Catalogue of the Names of ſuch young Women as to
this Authors knowledge haue beene within two or three yeares laſt paſt
tranſported to the Nunneries beyond the ſeas.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>. <hi>Anne M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>nfeild.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Miſtris <hi>Anderton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs <hi>Parker.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs <hi>Anne Gray.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Talbot.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Linſel.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Sydnam.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Percy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Gerard.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Floud.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Aſhton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Greffin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Halſal.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs <hi>Blimſtone.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iane Roe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Eueleigh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs <hi>Worthington.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Elizabeth Luſher.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bridget Lee,</hi> a kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching maid, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time
dwelling at the vpper end of Holborne.</item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Molineux.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="120" facs="tcp:3205:64"/>Mrs. <hi>Ingam</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Webbe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dorothy Stamp.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Blackſtones.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Elizabeth Powell</hi> of Holborne.</item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Ruckwood.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Lathom.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Forteſcue.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Winchcombe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Townely.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Townely.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mary Turner.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mary Smith.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Iones.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Owen.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs <hi>Clifton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sara Brewer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Grace Wire.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Atkins.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Drury.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Stanley.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Sanders.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Conniers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mrs. <hi>Abbington.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="list_of_agents_employed_for_conveying_women_to_overseas_nunneries">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:3205:64"/>
               <head>Factors employed for the conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouer of the ſaid Women
to the Nunneries.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>MAſter <hi>Hughes</hi> of London, a man very actiue in
perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the ſaid buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</item>
                  <item>Maſter <hi>Palmer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Spaniſh Iohn,</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly called <hi>The Deuils
fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor:</hi> or <hi>Forty pound Iohn,</hi> which name was giuen him for
coſening two gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of 40 pounds, whom he vndertook to
tranſport.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Smith.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A kinſman of Maſter <hi>Fiſher</hi> the
Ieſuit.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vdal</hi> of Gun-powder Alley.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Barbar.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iames Hart.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vincent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captaine <hi>Dak.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sherborne.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Langton,</hi> a Lancaſhire man.</item>
                  <item>Maſter <hi>Peeters.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Stubbes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Louet,</hi> a brother to the popiſh
Goldſmiths.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:3205:65"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:3205:65"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
